Friends, Romans,
countrymen, lend me your ears.
I come to bury Caesar, not to praise
[music] him. Julius Caesar is dead,
stabbed by a group of Roman senators,
including his friend Brutus, who feared
that Caesar had the ambition and the
ability to become a tyrant that would
destroy the Roman Republic. Mark Antony,
another friend of Caesar's, arrives
after the murder and is shocked and
saddened, but ultimately plays along
with the conspirators to save his own
skin. Brutus is going to go outside and
justify the assassination to the Roman
crowd and agrees to let Antony deliver a
eulogy, but only if he promises not to
condemn the conspirators. Antony agrees
and they all go outside to face the
people. Brutus speaks first, explaining
that even though he loved Caesar, Caesar
had to die because he represented a
danger to all free Roman citizens.
>> Had you rather Caesar were living and
die all slaves,
THAN THAT CAESAR WERE DEAD
TO LIVE ALL FREE MEN?
>> HE doesn't give specific examples of
Caesar's tyrannical ambitions, but
appeals to the crowd's faith in his own
honor and judgment and it seems to work.
At the end, the crowd cheers Brutus and
condemns Caesar. Then Antony steps
[music] up. Friends, Romans,
countrymen, lend me your ears. Antony's
facing a hostile, rowdy crowd, so he has
to get their attention right away.
Instead of the typical iambic rhythm of
da dum da dum, an unstressed syllable
followed by a stressed syllable, Antony
hits us with a stressed syllable right
away. Friends. In fact, the first three
words all begin with stressed syllables.
Boom, boom, boom. Now we're listening.
That first word is important to note. In
his speech, Brutus began with Romans,
appealing to the crowd's reason. Antony
starts with friends. He's aiming for an
emotional connection and friendship will
be a key theme in the speech.
>> I come to bury Caesar, not to praise
him. Yeah, if Antony were attached to a
lie detector right now, it would be
spiking. Praising Caesar is exactly what
he intends to do. That and condemn the
conspirators. But the crowd doesn't want
to hear praise of the would-be tyrant
and Antony vowed not to condemn the
assassins. His impossible rhetorical
mission in this speech, should he choose
to accept it, is to praise Caesar and
condemn the conspirators while appearing
to do the opposite.
>> The evil that men do
lives after them.
The good is often interred with their
bones.
So let it be with Caesar. These lines
seem to follow on from Antony's promise
not to praise Caesar, but they throw up
all kinds of red flags in the mind of
the listener. So we remember the bad
thing someone does, but often forget the
good. Is that supposed to be a good
thing? Shouldn't we seek to remember
someone in all their complexity? Subtly,
Antony gets the audience to start
thinking about the good Caesar did in
his life. In fact, he's associating good
with the bones, the corpse of Caesar
that is right now in front of them,
while evil he associates with the men
who still live. Who exactly is asking
the crowd to forget the good Caesar did?
The answer comes right away in the
second part of that last line.
>> The noble Brutus hath told you Caesar
was ambitious.
If it was so,
it was a grievous fault,
and grievously hath Caesar answered it.
Now, Antony's not saying Caesar was
ambitious. He's saying that Brutus is
saying that Caesar was ambitious. This
is a trick he'll return to many times.
In the third line, he's opening up that
door of doubt even further by saying if
it were so, suggesting that there's a
chance it's not so, that Brutus is
mistaken or lying. If Caesar was
ambitious, it's a criminal fault and the
appropriate price is death. If he wasn't
ambitious, well, what does that make the
killing?
>> Here, under leave of Brutus and the
rest, for Brutus is an honorable man, so
are they all, all honorable men, come I
to speak in Caesar's funeral. Damian
Lewis is so brilliant delivering this
speech. In this whole first part, he
hasn't betrayed his true goals as
Anthony. He's been gently pulling the
crowd, his friends, into his
perspective, and yet you can feel that
there's something brewing in him.
>> Here, the way he delivers that word,
another stressed syllable to start the
line, it's explosive, but his head
barely moves. Lewis fixes your attention
like a general demanding obedience, but
before you have a chance to register
that, he shifts back into the friendly
demeanor. For this part of the sentence,
which is really a parenthetical
interruption, Lewis's head loosens and
moves around as if to communicate the
fact that Brutus and his conspirators
are honorable is so obviously true, it
almost doesn't need mentioning, but
under the cover of this aside, Anthony
has just laid his trap.
>> He was my friend,
faithful and just
to me.
But Brutus says he was ambitious,
and Brutus
is an honorable man. There's that word
friend again. What is a friend after
all? Faithful, just. Notice how Lewis
lights up at that word, just. It's an
odd way to describe a friend, but it is
how you describe a good ruler. Here, we
have a repetition of the premise that he
slipped in so casually before. He ties
Brutus's honor to Brutus's assertion
that Caesar was ambitious. Really,
Brutus did this himself in his own
speech, but Anthony is making it plain.
He's creating a causal link between
Brutus's honor and the truth value of
his assertions. Now, he doesn't have to
attack Brutus directly, he can
interrogate the truth of what he says
and accomplish the same goal.
>> He hath brought many captives home to
Rome whose ransoms did the general
coffers fill.
Did this in Caesar seem ambitious?
When that the poor have cried, Caesar
hath wept.
Ambition should be made of sterner
stuff. Yet Brutus says he was ambitious,
and Brutus is an honorable man. Brutus
didn't bother to give examples of
Caesar's ambition, but Antony provides
examples of ways in which he wasn't
ambitious. He increased public funds for
Rome's welfare. He cried for the poor
like an empathetic friend. That empathy
is evoked by a rhythmic association
between Caesar and the poor, which Lewis
emphasizes.
>> When that the poor have cried, Caesar
hath wept.
>> Antony uses a rhetorical question to
further engage the audience, and then
encourages them to imagine ambition as
something stern and cruel. Of course,
these examples are not really
incompatible with ambition. But hey, if
the audience can't see through a
populist leader's crocodile tears,
they're not going to see through
Antony's manipulations, either. You all
did see that on the Lupercal, I thrice
presented him a kingly crown, which he
did thrice refuse.
Was this ambition?
Yet Brutus says he was ambitious, and
sure he is an honorable man. Now, in a
society that thinks of itself as a
republic, an ambitious autocrat would
probably be smart to refuse a crown. But
Antony knows that this crowd will read
Caesar's actions as the exact opposite
of ambition, and he helps the
information go down easy with three
lines of nearly perfect iambic
pentameter. By the time we get to the
final refrain, Lewis's sarcasm is hard
to miss, but now it's inflected with
rage. There's so much contempt in that
word, "Sure." It's likely that Antony is
genuinely angered by Caesar's death, but
the The display is also a rhetorical
tactic. He's not instructing the
audience to get angry. He introduces a
premise that they buy into without
question. And as the dissonance grows
with each repetition between that
premise and the evidence he presents, he
gradually fills the gap with his own
seemingly spontaneous, authentic
emotion. Anthony worked to elicit a
dramatic identification at the start,
and now he's used that to trap the
audience into mirroring his anger. I
speak not to disprove what Brutus spoke,
but here I am to speak what I do know.
You all
did love him once.
Not without cause.
What cause withholds you then to mourn
for him? This is a risky move. Not only
is Anthony telling the audience how they
felt about Caesar, he's redirecting a
little bit of that anger and frustration
toward them. So far, the speech has been
all about creating identification with
the audience. Now, he's creating
distance to suggest, like a parent
might, that maybe they should feel a
little guilty for cheering the murder of
someone they once loved, maybe even a
little complicit. O judgment, thou art
fled to brutish beasts and men have lost
their reason.
Here Anthony moves into a higher poetic
register, suggesting even more
forcefully that the audience lost their
reason. That just minutes ago, they were
acting like beasts. He's even slyly
comparing them to Brutus, whose honor
has been discredited. Why doesn't the
audience get defensive here? Well, if
Anthony had started with these lines,
they likely would have. But, he's earned
their trust, and now he's spending that
coin. And his challenges are softened by
the way he says them. Instead of a
direct accusation, he uses a rhetorical
question. Instead of scolding the
audience directly, he's addressing the
abstract concept of judgement. But this
section depends so deeply on the
performance, and Lewis shows us why it
really works. His anger here is not the
anger of condemnation or revenge, which
he seems to have for Brutus. The anger
that spills out into the audience is the
anger of grief. And that kind of anger
doesn't elicit anger in response, it
elicits pity. Bear with me.
Miraculously, Antony, or really well,
Shakespeare achieves the best of all
worlds here. He simultaneously places
Antony below, with, and above the
audience. They feel sorry for him, sorry
with him, and sorry for their own
thoughtless response to the death of his
friend and theirs. Now, all he needs to
do is pause and let the audience decide
for themselves who deserves their
sympathy and who deserves their fury. I
don't think the verdict will be a
surprise for Mark Antony.
My heart is in the coffin
there with Caesar.
And I must pause till it come back to
me.
>> [music]
[snorts]
>> Hey everybody, thank you so much for
watching. This episode was brought to
you by Squarespace, the all-in-one
website platform for entrepreneurs to
stand out and succeed online. To get
started, you can use Blueprint AI,
Squarespace's AI-enhanced website
builder to get a fully customized site
in just a few steps, or choose from
their library of professionally designed
templates that are sleek [music] and
engaging. Every website you make will be
optimized for SEO, so you'll show up
more often in search results, [music]
and you can do so much within
Squarespace like creating members-only
content, [music] videos, blogs, courses,
creative work that you can monetize via
one-time payments [music] or
subscriptions. The bottom line is that
Squarespace is going to make a home for
your products or your work that looks
and feels [music] professional.
Something that will impress your
customers and fans. Head over to
squarespace.com for a free trial. And
when you're ready to launch, go to
squarespace.com/nerdwriter
for 10% off your first purchase. Thanks,
guys. I'll see you next time.