For 250 years, there was a Japanese
secret hiding deep in the state archives
of Venice, Italy. A secret not a single
person in Japan knew about. A secret
contained in these two letters. [music]
They were found in 1873 during the
Iwakura Embassy, a Japanese [music]
diplomatic mission that traveled through
the US and Europe to study the West's
political and economic systems. You see,
Japan had only recently emerged from
centuries of self-imposed isolation.
Now, it wanted to modernize, so it sent
off a delegation to learn how the rest
of the [music] world was doing that. 2
years into that mission, they arrived in
Venice and found something they didn't
expect. At 9, [music] we boarded a boat
and went to the library at the city
archives. The library contains two
letters sent by Otomo of our country.
They [music] were both written in Latin
on western paper and at the end they
bore handwritten signatures written in
pen. Ambassador Iwakura bade me make
copies of them and they are appended
[music] below. Okay, what is so
important about these letters? Well, two
things. One, their dates and two, the
person who wrote them. In his diary, Kou
Kunake identifies that person as an
emissary of this man, Otomo Serene, a
Japanese feudal lord of the Bango
province in Kyushu. That's this region
here. In 1578, [music] Serene converted
to Christianity and later sponsored a
mission that would send four Japanese
teenagers halfway across the world to
meet the Pope [music] in Rome. That
mission came to be known as the Teno
Embassy and it was the first ever
Japanese delegation to visit Europe.
[music] As far as Kou or anyone knew,
the Teno Embassy was the only mission
from Japan to Europe before the
country's recent reopening. [music] So,
the letters simply had to be from them.
There was only one problem. The dates
don't match. Now Kou sees this 30-year
discrepancy, but he doesn't really know
what to make of it. His confusion
centers around the mysterious man
identified in the signature he copied, a
man named Hasakura Roiman. This Hakura
may have been one of Autotomo's
followers with a particularly strong
faith. [music] Some say he was a
retainer of Date Masamune of Sendai, but
there seems to be some doubt as to
whether Date was even in contact [music]
with the West. I record merely what
we've heard and leave the matter to the
consideration [music] of historians. You
can't blame Kou for not solving this
mystery. In 1873, there was likely no
one on planet Earth who knew why
Hakuraan was in Venice in 1615. To
understand why that is, you have to
understand what was happening in Japan
in the early 1600s. Now, there are three
periods of Japanese history relevant to
this story. The Senoku period, the Edeto
[music] period, and the Maji era. Now,
I'll try to keep this brief. The Sangoku
period from 1467 to6003 was a time of
almost constant civil war between
regional Japanese lords vying for
dominance. In 1600, one of those lords,
Tokugawa, finally achieved that
dominance at the famous battle of
Sakiara. And three years later, he
united the country and established the
Tokugawa shogunit, which ruled Japan in
a time of relative peace for over 250
years. That's the Edeto period. Finally,
in 1868, the shogunit was overthrown in
the name of the emperor Magi, launching
Japan into a period of rapid
modernization. And that period is called
the Magi era. Okay. Now, let's put the
events of our story onto this timeline.
The Iakura embassy takes place between
1871 and 1873. [music]
During the Magi era, that's when the
letters are found. The Teno embassy with
those four teenagers happens between
1582 and [music] 1590 near the end of
the Sangoku period. And Hasakura Roaman
writes his letters in 1615 and 1616
respectively almost a decade into
[music] the Edeto period. Why did Kou
know about the Teno embassy but not
about Hasakura? [music]
It doesn't become clear until you add
one more historical period to this
Japanese timeline.
In 1549, Christianity arrived in Japan
with the coming of Francis Xavier, a
Spanish priest and co-founder of the
Jesuit order. Of course, the Portuguese
had already been in the country for 6
[music] years by then, and no doubt they
were Christian. But Xavier was the first
major missionary to arrive in Japan. He
inaugurated what is sometimes called
Japan's Christian century, though in
reality it wasn't quite as long as that.
Since Japan in the Sangoku period with
all those waring states lacked a central
authority, Christian missionaries like
Xavier were able to make inroads [music]
in a number of regions, primarily
southern ones with even a handful of
regional lords converting to this new
faith. Lords like Otomo Serene, the
sponsor [music] of the Teno embassy.
Some of those conversions were genuine
while others, well, they were
opportunistic. A number of Japanese
lords welcomed or [music] at least
tolerated the missionaries as a way to
secure good trading relationships with
Europe. [music] particularly the
Portuguese. As is often the case, the
spiritual was entwined with the economic
and both the Jesuits and the Japanese
use that fact to their advantage. A
perfect example of that is the Teno
[music] embassy. For the Jesuits,
parading baptized Japanese teenagers
through the streets of Rome showed that
the mission in Japan was a fruitful one,
worthy of more [music] resources. For
Serene and the Japanese lords who
sponsored it, the embassy strengthened
trade ties, promising more [music]
wealth and weapons. It was a good deal
while it lasted. I said before that
Tokugawa unified [music] the country,
but he was really the last of three
great unifiers. The first of these, Oda
Nobunaga, was generally welcoming to the
missionaries. But [music] the second,
Toyotomy Hideoshi, came to distrust them
and viewed the impact of their work as
destabilizing to the social fabric. In
[music] 1587, he issued an edict to
expel all missionaries. It wasn't
rigorously enforced, but it was a
harbinger [music] of things to come. In
1596, a Spanish gallion shipwrecked on
the coast of Kochi and its pilot
intimated to Japanese officials that
Christian missionaries were a vanguard
for a future military conquest. Whether
this was true or not, it was the wrong
thing to say. In response, Hideoshi
ordered 26 [music] Catholics to be
crucified on a hill in Nagasaki. Almost
all of those 26 [music] were in fact not
Jesuit, but Franciscan. In the 1890s,
this rival Catholic order launched their
own mission in Japan, and they were less
discreet [music] than the Jesuits, more
openly evangelical, which was a
dangerous thing to be in Hideoshi's
later [music] years. Luckily for all the
missionaries, Tokugawa Yasu, the third
and final great unifier, [music] was
more tolerant of Christianity than his
predecessor, at least for a while.
It was during this period of tolerance
in6002
that a certain Franciscan frier arrived
in Japan. His name was Luis Sautello and
he is the first main character of our
story. [music] In her great book on this
subject, a Japanese mission to 17th
century Rome. Katherine M. Luchesy draws
a fascinating portrait of Sautello. Born
to a prominent family [music] in
Sevilla, he studied philosophy and
theology at the University of Salamanca
before becoming a Franciscan priest with
a passion for missionary work. He was
first sent to Manila but long [music] to
go to Japan. So much so that he taught
himself the language while still in the
Philippines and even translated the
catechism into [music]
Japanese. Despite repeated warnings of
danger and persecution, Sautello finally
[music] made it to Japan in6002 and in
short order erected four convents
[music]
in four cities. He opened hospitals for
the sick and leper colonies and made the
acquaintance of powerful people [music]
including the new shogun Tokugawa.
But it was a chance meeting with another
Japanese lord that would change
Sautello's life forever. In 1611, Date
Masamune, remember that name from Kou's
diary? Date was in Edeto looking for a
place to treat his sick European
concubine, and he found Luis Sautello's
hospital. After healing the concubine,
Date and Sautello hit it off. [music]
Not long after, Sautello traveled to
Date's domain in Oshu and preached the
[music] gospel to this powerful Japanese
lord. Up here in this northeastern
province far from the Jesuit power
center in Nagasaki, Sautello saw a great
opportunity for the Franciscans, the
chance to establish a new dascese,
maybe, who knows, with himself as
[music] the bishop. For that, however,
he would need the approval of the pope.
It's unclear how deep D's interest in
Christianity actually was, [music] but
he was certainly interested in
increasing the power and influence of
his domain. [music]
One way to do that was to establish his
own relationship with the European
empires, particularly Sautello's native
Spain. [music]
Perhaps a trading port to rival those in
the south, perhaps [music] one in his
backyard. You can see that the interests
of these two enterprising men, though
not quite the same, were aligned. So, a
plan was hatched, a ship was built, a
new embassy was created. All Date
Masamune needed was someone to lead this
mission alongside Father Sautello, a
loyal vassel, a representative, a
samurai by the name of Hakura Roaman.
[music]
Hey everybody, thank you so [music] much
for watching. This episode was brought
to you by Squarespace, the all-in-one
website platform for entrepreneurs to
stand out and succeed online. To get
started, you can use Blueprint AI,
Squarespace's AI enhanced website
builder to get a fully customized site
in just a [music] few steps, or choose
from their library of professionally
designed templates that are sleek and
engaging. Every website you make will be
optimized for SEO, so you'll show up
more often in search results. And you
can do so much within Squarespace, like
creating membersonly content, videos,
blogs, courses, creative work that you
can monetize via one-time payments or
subscriptions. The bottom line is that
Squarespace is going to make a home for
your products or your work that looks
and feels professional, something that
will impress your customers and fans.
Head over to squarespace.com for a free
trial. And when you're ready to launch,
go to squarespace.com/nerdwriter
for 10% off your first purchase. Thanks,
guys. I'll see you next time.