There is a pain that is harder than death.
It is not torture.
It is not humiliation.
It is when you know who killed your
loved one, yet you must walk up to
him, kneel down, and apologize for the dead.
No sorrow is allowed, no anger is
allowed, not even silence is allowed.
Because silence itself is an
attitude, attitude is evidence,
and evidence means death.
The only thing you can do is to
suppress all hatred into a flawless
smile,
and live on day by day.
Autumn, twenty-three A.D.
News spread from Wancheng.
Liu Xiu's elder brother, Liu Yan,
was killed by Emperor Gengshi, Liu Xuan.
No trial, no battlefield, no
dignified way to die at all.
He didn't die in battle;
he was disposed of.
Like a piece that must be removed
from the board.
The charges were fabricated, and it
was too fast for the execution of a
decorated general.
Liu Xiu was leading troops away.
Two months ago,
he defeated four hundred twenty
thousand with three thousand at Kunyang.
The whole world was whispering his name.
When he heard the news,
he was surrounded by Emperor
Gengshi's men.
Colleagues in name,
but in reality, they were eyes
watching him.
He had to make a judgment in a very
short time.
How he reacted next
would decide his life or death.
He was twenty-eight that year.
The longest endurance in Chinese
history begins right here.
To tell this story clearly, we must
go back to the start.
Liu Xiu was the ninth-generation
grandson of Liu Bang.
In his time
this lineage was worthless now.
The Han Tui'en Decree eroded it
over generations.
By Liu Xiu's father, Liu Qin, he
was just Nandun's magistrate.
His father died early,
and the brothers grew up farming in
rural Nanyang.
But Liu Xiu had an extraordinary brother.
Liu Yan was a born leader.
Bold, generous, and unconventional,
he loved befriending heroes.
He always spoke of restoring the Han.
Such talk was treason under the Xin
Dynasty, but Liu Yan was fearless.
He felt destined for great things.
Liu Xiu was more like a shadow.
Silent, cautious, and unassuming.
He loved reading.
His ambition was to be a Zhijinwu
and marry Yin Lihua.
A Zhijinwu led the capital's guards.
It sounded grand,
but it was just a prestigious
military post.
One aimed for the throne, the other
for security chief.
Standing together, everyone thought
the elder brother would be the one
to succeed.
Chaos erupted at the end of the Xin Dynasty.
Rebel armies like the Chimei and
Lulin erupted.
Liu Yan seized the moment,
revolting with his brother and
Nanyang elites.
Liu Xiu rode an ox into his first battle;
he didn't even have a horse.
Liu Yan was a formidable fighter.
He was a gifted warrior and a
charismatic leader.
His army grew, and his prestige
soared, so much that the Lulin
leaders grew uneasy.
February, twenty-three A.D.
Rebel forces gathered to choose an emperor.
By merit and fame, Liu Yan was the
best choice.
But the Lulin army refused.
They had no ties or loyalty to the
Liu family,
only a temporary alliance of convenience.
They wanted a puppet, not a strong ruler.
If Liu Yan took power and then
purged them,
none of them would escape.
Choosing the weak Liu Xuan as
Emperor Gengshi, Liu Yan became
Grand Minister over the Masses.
top of the Three Excellencies.
As civil head, he was the empire's
nominal leader.
Yet this title didn't fix the core issue.
It wasn't about the rank,
but about what everyone could see:
if Liu Yan wanted to,
he was more qualified for the
throne than Liu Xuan.
Liu Xuan was propped up,
but Liu Yan earned his way there.
These two types of legitimacy carry
vastly different weight.
A puppet emperor who was pushed
onto the throne...
...never fears external enemies the most.
External enemies can be fought together.
He mostly fears the more
emperor-like man beside him.
Liu Yan's very existence denied Liu Xuan.
Worse yet, Liu Yan didn't hold back;
he always resented Liu Xuan
becoming emperor.
His words and actions showed no
respect for Liu Xuan.
He probably felt that with his own
merit and strength...
...no one could touch him.
He was wrong.
Lulin generals Zhu Wei and Li Yi
kept whispering in Liu Xuan's ear.
If Liu Yan isn't removed...
He'll be trouble.
Insecure, Liu Xuan heard this
often, turning murderous.
They found an opportunity.
Citing a subordinate's misconduct,
they summoned Liu Yan and seized
him immediately.
...and killed.
Upon hearing this, Liu Xiu was stuck.
With little power, he had no way to resist.
His subordinates included spies
planted by Emperor Gengshi.
Every move he made was under surveillance.
After Liu Xuan killed Liu Yan, the
next person to be watched was him.
If Liu Xiu showed dissatisfaction,
grief, or any signs of potential
revenge,
...he'd soon follow his brother.
So Liu Xiu did what might have been
the most painful thing in his life.
He rushed to Wancheng.
He forwent mourning.
No memorial tablet, no word on the
body, he didn't even head back to
his tent.
He went to see Liu Xuan and knelt,
apologizing for his brother's crimes.
Stating Liu Yan acted improperly
and he failed to discipline him, he
asked for punishment.
History books recorded his posture
during that audience...
taking the blame.
He took all the faults upon his own head.
He never mentioned the wrong.
These words, written about a man
who just lost his brother, every
single word is like a knife.
He was so humble that Liu Xuan had
no reason to kill him.
Liu Xuan prepared two plans.
If Liu Xiu caused trouble, he'd
handle him too.
But Liu Xiu's reaction was surprising.
His brother was just killed, yet he
came to apologize.
Liu Xuan was unsure how to react.
He made Liu Xiu the Marquis of
Wuxin, granting him a title but no
real power.
This wasn't a reward.
It was appeasement, and also a test.
After making him a marquis, he'd
see how the man moved next.
After returning to his quarters, he
didn't dare to cry.
Not just in public, he didn't even
dare to cry when alone.
He didn't know if there were ears
behind the walls...
Outside the tent, he ate, met
people, and handled official
business normally.
As if the death didn't affect him.
The Book of the Later Han describes
him then: 'Eating, drinking,
talking, and laughing.'
Six characters.
They capture the whole process of a
man crushing his own bones and
swallowing them.
In those months, grief itself was
evidence of a crime.
Stop and think about that scene for a moment.
His own brother was murdered.
The killer sat across, offering a toast.
He couldn't refuse or stop smiling,
and he couldn't let that smile crack.
He had to not only smile naturally
but convince everyone he had truly
let it go.
This wasn't just for a day or two.
This went on for months.
A performance for survival that
could never falter.
What sustained this performance
wasn't character or background.
It was judgment.
It was his ability to make cold
calculations even in extreme pain.
Turning against them now...
...would be a dead end.
Crying now would be a dead end.
Letting anyone see his true
emotions would be a dead end.
Only by staying alive could there
be a future.
History has many examples.
Goujian slept on wood, Han Xin
crawled through legs, and Sima Yi
faked illness to fool Cao Shuang.
But when they endured,
at least they had a moment of
solitude,
a corner where they could grit
their teeth unseen.
Liu Xiu lacked even that luxury.
His environment of endurance was
fully exposed.
Any second of losing control
would cost him his life.
During Liu Xiu's days in Wancheng,
He made another decision that
disheartened his followers.
He deliberately distanced himself
from those close to Liu Yan, with
no meetings or contact, drawing a
clear line.
Wasn't cold
protection.
He saw Liu Xuan tracking Liu Yan's men
to determine the next leader.
If Liu Xiu kept associating with
these people,
it would tell Liu Xuan that this
group still had a leader and might
gather together again.
He had to make Liu Xuan believe one thing:
After Liu Yan, none would follow.
"Not daring to be first." These
five words in history aren't humility;
they're survival.
Disappointing his followers was
better than a purge.
So he bore all the pain alone,
while making his brother's
followers think he was heartless.
Enduring the enemy's suspicion on one hand,
and the heartbreak of his followers
on the other.
Some people looked down on him
because of this, thinking Liu Xiu
was nothing special.
His brother was killed, yet he
showed no reaction;
he wasn't cut out for greatness.
Later, they realized they were
wrong, terribly wrong.
When would this endurance ever end?
Liu Xiu waited for several months,
until Liu Xuan's guard slowly lowered.
Then he seized a chance and
volunteered for Hebei.
Hebei was no simple territory.
Away from the court, it was ruled
by powerful clans.
Order shattered, anyone who could
restore the region,
could grow their own roots.
Titled General Who Breaks the
Barbarians, acting Grand Marshal,
holding the powers of the Grand Marshal.
He crossed the Yellow River to
pacify Hebei, yet was given very
few actual troops.
not even a decent unit at all.
Liu Xuan thought this was exile;
Liu Xiu knew it was a chance to breathe.
In Wancheng, his every move was
evidence against him.
In Hebei, he could finally
reorganize people,
rebuild relationships,
and have his own judgment once again.
To Liu Xiu, the key to Hebei wasn't the land;
it was distance.
Distance is space, and space is possibility.
Endurance isn't about keeping one's
head down forever, but waiting for
the chance to look up.
This was Liu Xuan's greatest mistake.
Returning to the word "endurance,"
many people interpret it as a
virtue, as if endurance itself is
worthy of praise. It's not.
Endurance is never the goal;
it's a means to an end.
Those months Liu Xiu endured
weren't because of good character
or a broad vision.
He endured
because he maintained his judgment
even in extreme pain, calculating
the probability of life and death
at every step,
and the gain difference between
acting now or later.
The truly terrifying person isn't
the one in a rage
but the one who hates to the bone
yet can still keep a smile in the
right place.
The former is just venting emotions;
the latter is already planning the future.
Looking back at this path:
suppressing his tears at the news,
rushing to Wancheng, and kneeling
to his enemy to apologize for his brother,
taking a marquisate with no power
giving thanks for a great favor.
For months after, eating and
laughing as if all was well.
avoiding his brother's followers
convincing all he was useless.
Finally, the moment Liu Xuan let
his guard down,
Volunteering for Hebei, none were
impulsive or resigned.
Every step was on a blade's edge.
every misstep would have been a
dead end.
He traded months of humiliation for
his life,
and now he's ready to trade that
life for the whole world.
Wancheng taught him one thing:
survival is not victory.
Survival is just earning the right
to place another bet.
Next stop, Hebei.
There's no emperor there to back him up,
no elder brother to pave the way,
and no ready-made army at his command.
Only a fragmented land, a people
who don't know who to trust,
and a decision that's about to
change everything.
The true story of Liu Xiu is only
just beginning from there.