The series is called The Dance of Death.
It was designed by Hans Holbein the
Younger — who lived from 1497 to 1543
— while he was working in Basel, somewhere
between 1523 and 1526.
Holbein drew the designs; the astonishing
fineness of the cutting belongs to a
master block-cutter named Hans
Lützelburger, whose work has been called,
quite simply, the most marvelous woodcuts
ever made.
By most accounts Lützelburger died around
1526, before the book ever reached print —
the craftsman who gave Death its face met
Death first.
The first edition appeared in Lyon in
1538, published by the Trechsel brothers
under a French title — Les Simulachres et
Historiées Faces de la Mort, the images
and storied faces of death — and it
held forty-one woodcuts.
People could not get enough of it.
There were eleven editions before 1562,
and across the century perhaps a hundred
more unauthorized copies and imitations.
An old churchyard tradition had been
shrunk down, printed, and let loose across
Europe.