When you first leaf through the series,
the premise looks simple, even repetitive.
Into one ordinary moment after another — a
throne room, a study, a day in the
fields — strides the same uninvited guest:
a skeleton.
Death has come, and Death always wins.
But look at how he behaves, and the
simplicity falls away.
Holbein's Death is not a solemn, hooded
reaper.
He is a performer, and the joke is
always tailored to his victim.
He turns into a kind of dispenser of
justice — denouncing greed and the abuse
of power.
He robs the rich man of his money
before he takes his soul.
He boldly hauls an abbot away by his
vestments.
He skewers a knight.
For the nobility, Death arrives as an
opponent who simply cannot be beaten.
In one scene after another, he doesn't
merely take the powerful — he mocks the
very thing they lived for, and more often
than not he holds up an hourglass to
do it.
That little glass runs through the series
like a refrain.
And then he reaches the people who never
had any power at all — and something
strange happens to his manner.