To feel why that matters, step back into
the world that made these prints.
The "dance of death," the danse macabre,
was already an old idea — a procession
of the living led away by the dead,
painted across the walls of charnel houses
so a whole town could file past it.
Its message was blunt and democratic:
whatever your rank, Death is the great
equalizer, and every class distinction is
wiped out the moment he takes your hand.
Holbein inherited that idea — and
sharpened every edge of it.
He was working in Basel in the 1520s,
a city right on the fault line of
the Reformation, and what he made was less
a gentle memorial than what scholars call
a reformist satire: the old allegory,
re-pointed.