And now we come to the Ploughman.
Among all these scenes of Death the
tormentor — Death the thief, Death the
mocker, Death who drags an abbot and
unseats a king — there is one that
is utterly different in tone.
A peasant works his field behind a team
of tired horses at the end of the
day.
And the figure beside him, helping to
drive the horses on, helping him finish
the very last furrow — that figure is
Death.
Here he is not a thief at all.
He is a companion.
He is almost a kindness, easing an
exhausted man toward the end of his row,
toward rest.
Sit with the contrast.
For the pope, the rich man, the knight,
Death is an ambush and a humiliation.
For the man who owns nothing but his
labour, Death is mercy.
The same skeleton, the same series, the
same artist — and two opposite meanings,
depending entirely on which rung of the
ladder you happen to stand on.