So which is the real Dance of Death?
Here the interpretations split, and both
have weight.
The traditional reading is the gentle one.
This is a memento mori: Death comes for
everyone, pope and ploughman alike, so
prepare your soul, because status counts
for nothing in the end.
Pious, universal, and perfectly at home in
a prayer book.
But notice who Death visits, and how.
He marches the pope, the cardinal, the
bishop, the abbot, the emperor and the
king to the front of the procession, and
he saves his cruelest jokes for exactly
the people who claimed to stand above the
crowd — and closest to God.
Read that way, the series stops being a
soft reminder of mortality and becomes a
reckoning: Death as the one honest
official who cannot be bribed, flattered,
or outranked.
And yet — and this is where it
stays honest — Holbein doesn't simply hate
the Church.
Look closely and you'll find that the
humble preacher and the parish priest
escape his sarcasm entirely; they're shown
in sympathy with the poor.
His scorn isn't aimed at faith.
It's aimed at power.