this video is made possible by Nord VPNs
stop protecting your internet experience
today go to Nord VPN comm /by graphics
and use the code bio graphics to get 70%
off a three year plan and an extra month
for free protect yourself online today
and let's get into it
Venezuela what do you think of when you
hear that name we're guessing it's
something along the lines of crime
economic collapse and more crime a
penniless Petro dictatorship long ruled
by the United Socialist Party Venezuela
has become a byword for a failing state
yet not so long ago it was a rich robust
democracy there was the envy of Latin
America so how did we go from rich past
to current crisis what was the bridge
connecting these diametrically opposed
visions of Venezuela the answer the
larger-than-life personality of a single
man Hugo Chavez was a
once-in-a-generation politician coming
to power as a populist outsider running
against out-of-touch elites he managed
to oversee a wholesale reform of
Venezuela refashioning it in his own
bombastic image as president he
instituted unprecedented spending gave
freely to the poor
Harvard poverty rates and reduced infant
mortality at the same time though he
turns what was once a functioning
democracy into an autocratic vanity
project one that was doomed to failure a
Robin Hood twosome a classic Latin
American dictator to others this is the
life of Hugo Chavez the man who made
modern Venezuela
[Music]
if you are inventing the background
story for a socialist revolutionary
you'd be hard-pressed to come up with
anything better than Hugo Chavez's
actual life born on the 28th of July
1954 Chavez was the real deal a
dirt-poor kid born in a house with a
literal dirt floor not that shimmers
grunt there at a young age he and his
older brother Adan were sent to live
with their grandmother when it became
apparent that their teacher parents
couldn't afford to feed them still that
doesn't mean Shiva's early life was all
hard knocks and misery as a boy he was
semi famous around the outskirts of
barrenness a small city on the edge of
Venezuela's vast grasslands for his
ability to play baseball this was the
era of guys like Nestor latigo Chavez no
relation the venezuelan pitcher who made
it all the way to the San Francisco
Giants and Hugo was determined to follow
in his footsteps but baseball wasn't the
only influence floating around barriness
at that time during the 1960s and 70s
Venezuela had to deal with a handful of
communist insurgencies while these armed
groups weren't a patch on Colombia's
FARC or peruse Shining Path
they were still a fact of life it said
that the teenage savez was intrigued by
the guerrillas who roams the nearby
countryside even going so far as to read
the works of Karl Marx still that was
all just background to his current love
affair with baseball age 17 Chavez left
Baroness and enrolled at the Military
Academy in Caracas hit her there the
best baseball coaches and plans do train
up then drop out as soon as he was good
enough to play in the leagues but while
his pitching might have been good for
Baroness it wasn't good enough for
Caracas at some point the young boy from
the dirt-poor home was forced to abandon
his baseball dreams and that was how
Hugo Chavez found himself stuck on a
military track he had no interest in
following with a yearning for fame that
could never be fulfilled he graduated in
1975 at the bottom of his class
immediately after he joins the army and
was packed off to fight a Maoist
insurgent group in rural and SWAT agooo
to say this was depressing would be like
saying Schindler's List
is a trifle sad scheffers hated his time
in the army he hated being in the middle
of nowhere he hated fighting the
guerrillas and he hated the human rights
abuses his unit committed come 1977 he
felt he had more in common with the
guerrillas than the army and he was on
the verge of quitting when his older
brother dropped an unexpected bombshell
by now
Aaron was a radical university professor
but no one had realized quite how
radical in secret a darn had been
building links with the communist
insurgents when he heard about his
brothers worries he offered to arrange a
meeting not long after Hugo Chavez
finally met Douglas Bravo despite having
a name that sounds like military code
for the letters D and B Douglas Bravo
was in reality a former guerrilla now
preaching the use of Venezuela's oil
wealth to build a socialist utopia
together he and Traverse forms the
Bolivarian movement 200 secret cell
within the military dedicated to
overthrowing the government when the
time came luckily for them at that time
was just around the corner
[Music]
we're gonna pause and take a quick
history lesson now one that will
hopefully explain why a failed baseball
player succeeded at taking over
Venezuela to do that we need to focus on
two vital things in the country politics
and oil the discovery of black gold in
Venezuela took place in 1922 the yeah oh
well in the Maracaibo Basin suddenly
began to gush a hundred thousand barrels
a day it was the start of a process that
would eventually lead to Venezuela
having the largest proven oil reserves
on earth it was also the start of a
dangerously lopsided economy the damage
really began in 1943 when the military
rulers signed a law forcing all foreign
oil companies to hand over a huge cut of
their profits the revenue this generated
was so vast that the government felt no
need to further diversify the economy
and that would leave Venezuela very
vulnerable to price fluctuations in oil
but a petrol economy alone does not make
an unstable state no that took both oil
mania and some very unwise decisions
taken at the top in 1958
opposition leader rómulo betancourt
became president ending military rule
known as the father of Venezuelan
democracy
Betancourt had a lot going for him but
he was also operating in a time when
Latin America was very unstable across
the border Colombia was just emerging
from something known as la violencia a
decade of undeclared civil war between
the liberal and conservative parties
that had killed over a hundred and fifty
thousand needn't keep Venezuela as
parties from each other's throats bed
and gourd established that punch of a
GMO power sharing pact keeping the main
parties perpetually in office the Ponte
veggie smo was great in that it led to
stability but less great in that it
concentrated all power in the hands of a
very narrow Europeanized elite belonging
to one of two parties as a results if
things ever went wrong the people would
know exactly who to blame the good times
reached their peak in the 1970s after
the Arab oil embargo led to a surge in
demand for Venezuelan crude in 1975 then
President Carlos Andres Perez
nationalized oil production and it seems
as if the money would never stop rolling
in but that's the trouble with a
non-diversified
economy all it takes is a single Black
Swan events and everything can come
crashing down fittingly Venezuela's
Black Swan took the form of oil prices
in 1981 a so-called oil glut caused a
global price crash this kneecap to the
Venezuelan economy but by 1989 the
country was in crisis president perez
took a loan from the IMF promising to
end food and fuel subsidies as a
precondition it's at this point that the
other bird came home to roost thanks to
the puns over GMO Venezuela's elites
were now so totally removed from their
struggling countrymen that they didn't
realize they needed the food subsidies
to survive so when the government
suddenly took those subsidies away well
let's just say that the masses didn't
take kindly to it the Caracas owe
erupted On February 27th 1989 a
week-long orgy of rioting in Caracas it
devastated the city although the
government managed to retake the streets
they did so at a great cost by one
estimate security forces killed around
3,000 rioters in the aftermath a huge
anger began to swell against the elites
against the print of gee smoke in the
military this anger found an outlet from
that year Hugo Chavez and Douglas Bravo
had no problem recruiting soldiers into
their revolutionary cell by the time the
nighties got underway they had their own
private army
[Music]
On February the 4th 1992 regular
broadcasts on Venezuelan TV were
interrupted by a breaking news report a
military coup was underway as tanks
rolled up the streets of the
presidential palace stories poured in of
armed units seizing the cities of
Maracaibo and Valencia for a moment it
really looks like the plotters would
take power but only for a moment
somehow president Perez managed to
escape capture he went on TV and called
for people to defy the plotters shortly
after the tanks stopped their assault
the leader of the coup cuts a deal to
stand down provided he was allowed to go
on live TV and asked his followers to
lay down their arms that very night
Venezuela got its first glimpse of Hugo
Chavez despite having just led a failed
coup savez seemed calm before the
cameras even amused in a short speech he
declared the key words there were for
now or por ahora in Spanish coming from
this confidence officer the soldier who
looks not like the Europeanized elites
but like the mixed heritage massa
Venezuelans those two words did not
sound empty they actually sounded like a
promise in the aftermath of the coup
Jabez was thrown in prison but he
wouldn't be there long the coup attempts
had come at a time when memories of the
karakasa were still fresh when the
ruling classes were trusted about as
much as you'd trust a babysitting
service run by Jared Fogle in shrivels
Venezuelans didn't see a renegade Army
officer they saw a hope for their future
next year 1993 president burrows was
impeached for embezzlement and removed
from office when Rafael caldera took
office in 1994 he issued a blanket
pardon to the coup plotters on his
release Chevys became a celebrity the
soldier who'd taken a stand against
corrupt Perez during a 100 day tour of
Venezuela the former plotter met
thousands of ordinary people and
everywhere he went he took his promise
por ahora things were bad but only for
now he seemed to be saying trust me new
possibilities will arise again by the
time the 1998 elections rolled around
Chavez was the most popular man in the
country founding a party known as the
movement of the fifth republic he ran
for president and it was perfect timing
Jabez painted himself as someone neither
left nor right simply an outsider who
would drain the swamp in Caracas and
shake up the money two-party system that
ignored ordinary voters the
establishment played right into his
hands putting up a foreign educated
candidates who might as well have
campaigned from a literal ivory tower
the results were unambiguous on December
the 6th 1998 Chavez won the presidency
carrying 56% of the vote on ferry the
second 1999 he was inaugurated on a
platform of sweeping change the triumph
of the failed baseball star had dreamed
of when he launched his coup just seven
years earlier was finally here por ahora
was gone it was merely a horror the time
was now no one watching Chavez's
inauguration on TV could have guessed it
but a historic moment had just taken
place when Hugo Chavez finally left
office in the back of a hearse he would
leave behind a country that had changed
forever
now you might not have to worry about
someone plotting a coup against you but
you might have to worry about people
stealing your data online look if you're
buying things online and you're not on a
secure Wi-Fi spot you really should be
using a VPN and that's where today's
sponsor Nord VPN comes in now I know
it's tempting not to bother just sort of
hope for the best but really those
stories you hear about online about
people having their data stone and they
really do happen and you don't want to
make it easy for that to happen to you
whenever I'm browsing on unsecured Wi-Fi
I just keep a VPN on in the background
all the time so I don't have to worry
about anyone stealing my data but it's
not just about security you can also use
it to change the country you appear to
be and so you can get content that might
normally only be available in specific
geographic locations nor VPN it's also
super fast so watching a video is a
breeze there's no lag whatsoever if
you've ever thought VPNs were slow well
that's not the case with Nord VPN and
you can use it on all of your devices
very easily Android Chrome Windows Linux
and on six different devices with just
one account also there are no logs kept
at all unlike companies based in the EU
or the US nor VPN is over in Panama
so they just don't have to keep any logs
which is obviously great for your
privacy start protecting your internet
experience today go to Nord VPN comm
forward slash biographic sand use my
code bio graphics to get 70% off a
three-year plan and an extra month for
free protect yourself online today and
let's get back to it when shavers took
office he was more popular than any of
today's populace could dream of being
across 1999 his approval rating hovered
around a staggering 80% he was helped by
a tranche of reforms including a planned
ball of our 2000 a kind of Venezuelan
New Deal that poured money into
infrastructure spending and building
affordable homes but this populism
masked deeper machination 's as
President Chavez was able to call a
referendum on rewriting the Constitution
with people still pissed at Venezuela's
elites he won by a wide margin in the
boat deciding who would do the rewriting
Chavez again carried the day the result
was a constitution rewritten to give the
president's six-year terms and allow
immediate re-election it also abolished
the Senate enforced every elected
official to run again for office in 2000
or lose their seats when Chavez put this
to referendum on the 15th of December he
won again
it was the classical political trick of
ramming through major changes while you
still have that honeymoon glow before
people start to seriously question your
motivations and it works when the mega
election was held in July 2000 shadows
won a new six-year term and a new
National Assembly was returns that held
a Pro Chavez majority not long after the
Supreme Court was quietly stuffed with
Pro shove as judges
but while shivers was consolidating his
power life in Venezuela was stubbornly
refusing to improve in 1999 the economy
had shrunk by 7% the problems that had
led to Chavez's own 1992 coup still
haven't gone away and shiva's wasn't the
only former officer willing to change
the leadership through force early
warning signs came in 2001 when Chavez
unveiled a package of executive decrees
designs to wildly redistribute land and
wealth in Venice
Wailer then turned the business
community and the upper classes against
him then he started cozying up to Fidel
Castro's Cuba alienating the middle
class come 2002 Chevy's his support was
tanking no one even seemed to be sure
who is ruling for apart from himself it
was at this point that El Presidente did
something very stupid there shivers
announced moves that would effectively
place the state oil company under the
control of his own party the reaction
was swift and it was violence on April
the 11th nearly a million people marched
on the president's palace in Caracas to
protest instead they were met by Chavez
loyal gunman who opened fire
it was the Caracas Oh all over again and
an unknown number of people died that
same day the military removed Hugo
Chavez from power so you're not an
easier you can see that this video still
has about half of its runtime left so
the question therefore is well how did
Hugo Chavez survive the coup the answer
sheer luck the same day shivers was
arrested the military installed
businessman Pedro Carmona as head of an
interim government but Carmona seems to
have mistaken this for a blank check and
immediately suspended the Constitution
and dissolved the government in response
the military appears to have been like
our knife this guy's even crazier than
the last guy therefore they just hit the
undo button [\h__\h] owner was himself
deposed and Chavez returns the
president's palace by the very army that
had arrested him after a mere 47 hours
Hugo Chavez was back in control at first
he was contrite promising more
compromise in the future accepting that
had gone too far but this is Chavez
remember the guy of por ahora all it
learns from the 2002 coup was that the
time wasn't ripe to launch his complete
takeover of the government but when the
time came he would be more than ready
the moments of the Carmona coup
collapsed Venezuela became a country
bitterly divided into two camps those
who loved shivers and those who spat at
the very mention of his name
initially the second camp was biggest
Jabez was just too openly craving power
for powers sake even fired striking
workers who opposed him and replaced
them with non-union labor move way more
capitalists Roeder than socialist
revolutionary but then Fidel Castro had
a quiet word in traverses errands
everything changed
the Bolivarian missions named after
independence hero Simon Bolivar were
simple in their genius government body
is funded by rising oil prices were
charged with going into the slums of
Caracas and improving life for the poor
there were adult literacy programs free
community health care subsidized food
banks free houses for the destitute well
okay you might be thinking but that's
just the very poorest that surely can't
be enough voters to keep Chavez in power
right but the thing is yeah there were
enough of them rather the boom times
under the Punto effigy snow when all
that all money came rolling in well it
had only come rolling in for those at
the very top
by the time shivers took power a full
50% of Venezuelans were living in
poverty ignored and forgotten by the
elites with the Bolivarian missions
someone was finally paying attention to
them and it's here that we can see one
of fascinating contradictions of Hugo
Chavez on the one hands the missions
they were clearly cynical organized to
get masses of voters on his side but on
the other hands the missions did really
work millions were lifted out of poverty
millions were given opportunities that
long been denied to them imagine for a
moment that you were a Caracas slum
dweller who'd seen her life star remain
resolutely third-world even as the
elites enjoyed unparalleled luxury now
imagine a government suddenly coming
along that gets rid of your dirt floor
that can give you drinking water that
can give your son an education which you
really refuse to vote third the man who
gave you all of this
the popularity boost from the missions
allow Chavez to survive a 2004 recall
referendum by 2005 he was popular enough
that he launched a program of land
expropriations aimed at large estates
that same year laws were passed
effectively ending media freedom come
opposition was boycotting elections so
Pro Chavez politicians effectively won
every seat going and Chavez himself won
re-election as presidents
Chavez's last great move that year was
to found the United Socialist Party of
Venezuela effectively merging nearly all
the country's left-wing parties with his
own the president now had a stranglehold
on power in Caracas his opponents were
down the masses in love with him and all
voices of moderation was silenced he was
effectively a got a man upon whose
shoulders all power in his nation rested
and it's at this point that things begin
to get a little weird
[Music]
one of the interesting things about
savez we can only see with hindsight is
that be prefigured today's populist s'
like many of those running the world now
Chavez scorned normal media channels
instead preferring to communicate
directly with his followers he was
obsessed with touring the country giving
speeches that were rambling folksy
unscripted and often fantastically
vindictive he developed away with
insults once calling george w bush more
dangerous than a monkey with a razor
blade he dabbled in conspiracy theories
speculating too enraptured audiences
that the moon landings were faked that
secret us super weapons caused
earthquakes it was a technique we're all
too familiar with in the presence the
use of bomb bursts and taboo breaking to
distract attention from the seriously
evil crap that you're actually up to but
while today's populist severe COEs of
Hugo Chavez the original was just
light-years beyond anything Donald Trump
Boris Johnson or even Rodrigo Duterte
could dream of by the late 2000s rivers
had so effectively become the focal
point of Venezuelan governance that he
was followed everywhere by cameras his
loosest off-the-cuff remarks translated
into instant policy as if he were some
sort of medieval European King there was
the time he set the nation's clocks back
half an hour and a win more the time he
nearly declared war on Colombia live on
air we're not making laws up on the fly
he was launching into seven-hour rants
on his weekly show allo Presidente
covering everything from whiskey to
cosmetic surgery it's tempting to think
the post 2006 Chavez simply lost it or
that he was merely another Gaddafi a
weirdo at har to finally let his
weirdness come out but there is another
view one summed up by the former editor
of the news site Caracas chronicles in
Venezuela these outbreaks of weird had a
different meanings visible displays of
Chavez's untouchability there's an
ineffable creepiness to a society where
the leader never pays a political price
for what he says no matter how plainly
crazy or illegal it may be in other
words Chavez only acted so crazy because
he knew he could get away with it
and he wanted you to know that he could
get away with it despite all the outward
trappings of a Gaddafi style
dictatorship though we should be careful
to note that Chavez wasn't actually a
dictator at least not in the traditional
sense in his 14 years in office he never
once rigged an election he won nearly
every vote he took part in and he won it
fair and square
on the other hands when he did lose he
found let's say creative ways around the
results in 2007 for example Chavez
narrowly lost a referendum on greatly
expanding his powers
the next day billboards appeared around
Caracas with the slogan por ahora it was
a promise one that Chavez followed
through on over the next three years
all the failed referendums provisions
were passed one way or another either by
breaking them up and holding separate
referendums or by making the National
Assembly passed laws or by using
executive orders by 2010 Chavez said
everything had asked voters for back in
2007 so yeah shivers may never have
become a dictator in the literal sense
but nor was he a Democrat more a strong
man who used democracy to do
undemocratic things come 2010 Chavez had
secured the constitutional right to keep
running for new presidential terms
indefinitely anyone watching Venezuela
at the time it seems like the 56 year
old Chavez's could conceivably keep
ruling for another three decades little
did anyone know that he'd be gone in
barely a tenth at that time the first
signs of the illness they would kill
Hugo Chavez appeared in June of 2011
that month our Presidente was forced to
cancel a meeting of Latin American
leaders and fly to Cuba for emergency
surgery not long after he informed his
public that had been diagnosed with
cancer at first it seemed that
treatments in Cuba were a success come
2012 savez was still feeling strong
enough to run in presidential elections
and win a third term but it was just a
smokescreen deep down Chavez knew what
was happening and he began to make
preparations on October the 11th 2012
Chavez abrupt
appointed former bus driver nicolas
maduro as his vice president Maduro had
been in government for a while but he
was an outsider to it's real circles of
power and singularly uncharismatic to
boot it's been assumed Chavez appointed
him because he was the most dogmatic but
most likely to carry on the Bolivarian
revolution if something were to happen
to shove Eze not long after it did in
January 2013 Chavez was so well that he
missed his own inauguration leading to
confusion as to whether he was still
even legally president but that pretty
soon became a moot point on March the
5th 2013 Hugo Chavez died of cancer less
than a month later a special election
was held to decide who would replace El
Presidente after 14 years despite the
backing of all the media and despite the
goodwill the masses still felt towards
Chavez his vice president Nicolas Maduro
barely squeaked home with a mere fifty
point six percent of the vote yet
squeakin he did and the rest is just so
much painful history today it's easy to
look at the mess that is Venezuela and
judge Hugo Chavez harshly in many ways
his revolution really was a catastrophe
crime soared under his watch
turning Caracas from a relatively safe
city into one of the most dangerous
capitals on earth the economy too was as
neglected as during the pontiff edgy
smoke like the elites before him Chavez
simply took the oil money without
thinking leaving behind an economy so
dangerously unbalanced that even basic
foodstuffs Venezuela could produce
domestically had to be imported he
racked up huge debt with China as he
chased the middle classes away hundreds
of thousands moved abroad taking their
business skills with them so yes there
are a whole bunch of reasons you can
blame modern Venezuela on Chavez's rule
many reasons why you can see his legacy
as nothing but poison but that's not the
whole picture but the awful stuff Hugo
Chavez did it's worth remembering one
salient fact the people really did love
him not in the way North Koreans are
forced to love Kim jong-un gun points
but a real deep love that came from
Chavez being the only man
to ever listen to them and traverse'
earned this love he lifted millions out
of poverty
he gave the Forgotten masses path to
education means to improve their lives
in ways that never dreams another time
with a different personality Hugo Chavez
could have been remembered as
Venezuela's Franklin D Roosevelt the
first president to speak for the common
man sadly we don't live in that time and
Chavez didn't have a better personality
what he did have though was an
undeniably historic impact if history is
simply the story of men and women who
changed the world around them and then
Hugo Chavez will always remain one of
Venezuela's most important chapters for
better and for worse he changed his
nation more profoundly than anyone
likely will again for centuries so I
really hope you found that video
interesting if you did please do smash
that like button below do not forget to
subscribe also please do support this
show by supporting our fantastic sponsor
Nord VPN link below and thank you for
watching