welcome back to world history explored
today we will talk about Venezuela's
history which is often Tangled in blame
some say socialism ruined everything
others point to a harsh dictator who
devastated the poor and some highlight
the country's overdependence on oil by
now you've likely come across various
reasons for Venezuela's crisis each
colored by the speaker political stance
the truth is the situation is the result
of many complex factors
and it's hard to get a clear picture
because people often use the crisis to
push their own agendas so we dove into
the internet and consulted some
impartial researchers to uncover what
really went wrong in Venezuela's
history the history of Venezuela is
deeply rooted in its ancient past
archaeologists have uncovered evidence
of the earliest known inhabitants of the
region through leaf-shaped flake tools
and other implements found on the high
river Terraces of the pedral river in
Western Venezuela these artifacts dating
from 15,000 to 9,000 years BP include
spear tips from a site in Northwestern
Venezuela known as El Jobo other notable
sites such as Tama yellow muo and El
Jobo in Falone have also provided
insights into these early societies
these early inhabitants coexisted with
megap like megaterium glyptodon and
toxodon
around 9,000 to 7,000 years BP during
the meso Indian period these early
hunters and gatherers began shifting to
other food sources and establishing the
first tribal structures by the time of
the timoto kuika culture which
flourished in present day Merida
Venezuela the complexity of
pre-colombian societies was
evident the timoto kuika were known for
their well-planned permanent Villages
surrounded by irrigated fields and
equipped with water storage tanks their
houses were constructed from Stone and
wood with thatched roofs and they
practiced peaceful agriculture growing
crops like potatoes and
ulcos they also left behind works of art
including anthropomorphic Ceramics and
are credited with inventing the aripa a
staple of Venezuelan
cuisine in 1498 on his third trip to the
Americas Christopher Columbus sailed
near the or noo Delta and landed in the
Gulf of paria he was blown away by a
massive flow of fresh water that pushed
him off course and wrote to Isabella and
Ferdinand saying he felt like he had
found heaven on Earth he marveled at how
such a huge amount of fresh water was so
close to saltwater and he thought it was
either a sign of paradise or an
Incredible Discovery since he'd never
seen anything like it
before karacas founded in 1567 in the
central coastal region became a key
location due to its proximity to the
port of lagara its defensible position
in a mountain valley and its fertile
healthy climate by the late 18th century
some Venezuelans started resisting
colonial rule Spain's neglect of its
Venezuelan Colony sparked a growing
interest in learning among Venezuelan
intellectuals unlike other Spanish
territories Venezuela had more external
sources of information though only the
Manos Venezuelan Creole Elites had
access to good
education the Manos also known as gr
kaca because of their wealth were seen
as arrogant and insistent on maintaining
their privileges over the mixed race
Paro majority the term mantuanos is
still used in Venezuela to describe
someone who is
pretentious the first organized attempt
to overthrow colonial rule in Venezuela
happened in
1797 led by Manuel Gul and Jose Maria
espa inspired directly by the French
Revolution their movement was crushed
with the help of the mantuanos because
it pushed for drastic social changes
Francisco de Miranda a hero of the
French Revolution is closely linked with
the fight for independence in Latin
America he dreamed of an independent
Empire that would unite all the
territories formally under Spanish and
Portuguese control stretching from the
Mississippi River to Cape Horn he
imagined this empire being led by a
hereditary Emperor called the Inca as a
tribute to the great Inca Empire and
governed by a byic Camal legislature
Miranda also proposed the name Colombia
for this Empire after the Explorer
Christopher
Columbus with some informal help from
the British general Miranda attempted to
invade the captain SE general of
Venezuela in
1804 Britain was at war with Spain which
was Allied with Napoleon at the time in
November 1805 Miranda went to New York
and began secretly organizing a
filibustering expedition to liberate
Venezuela he hired a ship with 20 guns
renamed it Leander after his eldest son
and set sail for Venezuela on February
2nd
1806 however his attempt to land in okar
De La Costa was
unsuccessful Miranda spent the following
year in the British Caribbean waiting
for reinforcements that never arrived
when he returned return to Britain he
found more support for his plans from
the British government in 1808 a large
military force was assembled to attack
Venezuela led by Arthur Welsley
however when Napoleon invaded Spain the
situation changed turning Spain into a
British Ally as a result the force was
redirected to fight in the Peninsular
War
instead events in Europe played a key
role in leading to Venezuela's
Declaration of Independence the nap
aonic Wars weakened Spain's control over
its Empire and unofficially put Britain
on the side of the independence movement
in May 1808 Napoleon forced Ferdinand
iith of Spain to abdicate along with his
father Charles IV Napoleon then
installed his brother Joseph bonapart as
king of Spain this sparked Spain's own
War of Independence against French rule
even before the Spanish-American Wars of
Independence
began in response the Spanish resistance
formed the Supreme Central Yuna to
govern in the name of Ferdinand iith the
first significant defeat for Napoleonic
France came at the Battle of balen in
Andalusia in July 1808 where future
figures like Pablo Moro emerio urenia
and Jose Des San Martin fought against
French General Pier dupon despite this
Victory the French soon regained the
upper hand and advanced into southern
Spain forcing the Spanish government to
retreat to kadis there the Supreme
Central Yun dissolved itself and
established a five-person Regency to
manage the state until the full Cortez
of kadis could be
converted news of the events soon
reached karakas but it wasn't until
April 19th 1810 that the city's Council
or cabildo decided to follow the example
of the Spanish provinces from 2 years
earlier by declaring the First Republic
of
Venezuela other provincial capitals like
Barcelona Kuma Merida LA assension
barinas and truo quickly did the same
the newly formed yunta suprema de
karakas was made up of self-appointed
elite members who claim to represent the
paros free blacks and even slaves
however the new government struggled to
maintain its alliance with the paros who
still had unresolved issues with the
mantuanos
some Manos including a young 27-year-old
Simon Bolivar saw the creation of the
Yun as a step toward full
Independence the Venezuelan war of
independence kicked off happening at the
same time as the struggle in new
Grenada on December 17th 1819 the
Congress of angostura declared Grand
Colombia an independent nation after two
more years of fighting Venezuela gained
independence from Spain in 182 21 led by
its most famous figure Simone Bolivar
for a while Venezuela was part of the
Republic of grand Colombia along with
present day Colombia Panama and Ecuador
until 1830 when Venezuela broke away and
became its own sovereign
country sukra went on to liberate
Ecuador and served as the second
president of Bolivia Venezuela remained
part of gr Columbia until 1830 when
rebellion led by Jose Antonio pz led to
the Declaration of an independent
Venezuela on September
22nd pz became the first president of
the newly formed state of Venezuela the
wars of Independence were devastating
with Venezuela losing between a quarter
to a third of its population during
these two decades including about half
of those of European descent by 1830 the
population was estimated at around
800,000 the colors of the Venezuelan
flag holds symbolic meanings yellow
represents the land's wealth blue stands
for the sea that separates Venezuela
from Spain and red honors the blood shed
by the heroes of
Independence slavery in Venezuela was
abolished in
1854 the 19th century in Venezuela was
marked by political instability and
periods of dictatorial rule the yunta
ruled from 1948 to 1958 with Perez Yim
menz becoming the main power player
especially after chalo's mysterious
death during a botched kidnapping in
1950 when the UN lost the 1952 election
they ignored the results and installed y
menz as president however he was forced
out on January 23rd
1958 to stabilize the young democracy
the major political parties Aion
democratica copee and yion republicana
democratica minus the Communist Party
signed The punio Pact ensuring ad and
cop dominated Venezuelan politics for
the next four
decades during the presidencies of
ramulo beton Court 1959 to 64 his second
term and rul Leoni
1964-69 Venezuela faced significant
Guerilla movements most of which
disbanded under rafhael caldera's first
term 1969 to 74 caldera's 196 8 win
marked the first time a party other than
Democratic action cope took the
presidency through a democratic election
the new Democratic order wasn't without
its challenges Bon Court survived an
assassination attempt in 1960
orchestrated by Dominican dictator
Raphael truo while leftist groups
excluded from the Pont toio pact started
an Insurgency forming the Armed Forces
of National Liberation with backing from
the Communist party and Fidel Castro
in 1962 they attempted to destabilize
the military but failed beton Court also
introduced the beton court Doctrine
recognizing only governments elected by
popular vote in 1973 Carlos Andreas
Perez was elected president during an
oil boom which led to a spike in
Venezuela's income as oil prices surged
the oil industry was nationalized in
1976 leading to massive public spending
and increasing EXP external debts
however when oil prices plummeted in the
1980s the economy took a severe hit the
government's devaluation of the currency
in 1983 worsened living standards and
economic mismanagement Rising poverty
crime and political instability
followed economic crisis in the 1980s
and 1990s led to political turmoil the
caracazo riots in 1989 during Carlos
Andreas Perez's second term saw hundreds
killed by security forces in response to
economic austerity measures this unrest
fueled Hugo Chavez's February 1992 coup
attempt followed by another in November
of the same year Perez who had been
reelected in 1988 was impeached on
embezzlement charges in
1993 Ramon Jose Velasquez served as
interim president from 1993 to
1994 in March 1994 Chavez was pardoned
by President Rafael Caldera which
allowed him to re-enter politics Chavez
won the presidency in 1998 and was
reelected in 2000 2006 and 2012 he also
won a presidential referendum in 2004
maintaining power until his death in
2013 in recent years Venezuela has faced
severe economic collapse with shrinking
output and rampant hyperinflation
causing shortages of basic Goods like
food and medicine government
mismanagement and US sanctions have led
to a drastic drop in oil production and
underinvestment despite the easing of
some sanctions in 2023 the US reimposed
sanctions in 2024 due to Venezuela's
failure to meet Fair election conditions
and that's that for today's video If you
enjoyed this video make sure to hit that
like button and subscribe to our Channel
World History explored for more updates
on the latest movies and shows
don't forget to click the Bell icon so
you never miss an update from us thanks
for watching and we'll catch you in the
next one