Something unprecedented is taking place
right now in the Caribbean Sea. The
United States is currently deploying
more military assets to this theater
than at any other point in the 21st
century, and it's the largest
concentration of US military might in
the Western Hemisphere since the
country's invasion of Panama in 1989.
This time, however, the US military is
concentrating its forces just outside of
the territorial waters of Venezuela,
arguably the most antagonistic country
in the Western Hemisphere to American
interests. The US has deployed three
modern Arlayberg class guided missile
destroyers and one ticeroga class guided
missile cruiser along with at least one
nuclearpowered attack submarine just
offshore of Venezuela that all
collectively carry a strike package of
dozens to hundreds of Tomahawk cruise
missiles. If these Navy warships weren't
enough, they've also been joined by the
22nd Marine Expeditionary Unit as well,
consisting of the amphibious assault
ship USS Emojima along with its
complement of two transport and
logistical support ships. The USS Eojima
in particular is basically a
miniaturized aircraft carrier that was
captured by photographs on its way to
Venezuela with multiple Harrier attack
aircraft M22 Osprey assault helicopters
and Sakorski heavy lift helicopters all
on board. It can also along with its two
transport and logistical support ships
launch multiple hovercraft and
amphibious assault vehicles for armed
beach assaults under its aerial coverage
too. More than 2500 US Marines have been
deployed here with the 22nd. Along with
around 2,000 sailors belonging to the
naval complement with the destroyers,
the cruiser, and the submarine. And on
top of all of this firepower, the US has
also deployed a literal combat ship to
the theater as well. The USS Minneapolis
St. Paul, bringing the total number of
vessels deployed in the theater so far,
up to nine, while at least an additional
10 F-35 fighter jets have also been
deployed to airfields in Puerto Rico.
The Trump administration's officially
stated purpose for deploying all of
these assets nearby to Venezuela right
now is to simply conduct counternarics
operations and to halt the flow of drugs
from Venezuela coming into the United
States. But deploying warships and
nuclearpowered submarines armed with
tomahawk cruise missiles, Harrier
aircraft, F-35 fighters, and thousands
of Marines ready for a beach assault
appears to be wildly overkill for that
kind of a mission alone against drug
runners who most often use nothing more
advanced than motorized speedboats. Most
drugs enter into the United States today
through the Pacific coast anyway, while
a great deal more come in through air
shipments. None of which the flotillaa
being assembled off the coast of
Venezuela will be capable of stopping,
which has led to rampant speculation
that their ulterior objective may be
attempting to induce regime change
within Venezuela instead. By
overthrowing their president, Nicholas
Maduro, merely weeks before this
flotilla began being assembled, the US
government doubled the bounty it had
placed on Maduro's head from $25 million
to an unprecedented $50 million. the
biggest bounty that the US government
has ever put on a single individual's
head in history. To put how serious this
$50 million bounty recently placed on
Nicholas Maduro is in comparison, it's
double the bounty that the US has put on
other previous men on its most wanted
lists like Osama bin Laden, Saddam
Hussein, and the former leader of ISIS,
Abu Baky Albagghdaddy. All of whom
topped out on the US bounty list at just
$25 million by comparison. The US bounty
on Nicholas Maduro today is what it once
had placed on both Osama bin Laden and
Saddam Hussein together. And the US
doesn't recognize him as Venezuela's
legitimate president either. And Maduro
himself is far from the only man in
Venezuela with a high US bounty on his
head. His appointed Minister of the
Interior, Diastano Cababo Randon, now
has a $25 million bounty placed on his
head as well, equaling Osama bin Laden's
bounty. His defense minister, General
Vladimir Padrino Lopez, has a $15
million bounty, while his minister of
industry, Tariq Zidon Isami Madawa, has
another $10 million bounty, collectively
representing $100 million worth of
bounties placed on just these four
senior leaders of the Venezuelan
government alone. In July, the month
before all of these bounties were
dramatically increased, US President
Donald Trump signed a secret directive
that authorized the US military to
deploy force against Latin American
cartels that were designated by his
government as terrorist organizations,
which includes Venezuela's most infamous
criminal organization, Trenagua. This
secret directive has once again raised
the spectre of a 21st century
interpretation of America's Monroe
Doctrine, its historical justification
for militarily intervening in the
affairs of other states in the Americas.
The Trump administration accuses Maduro
and his close inner circle of secretly
running their own drunk cartel called
the cartel of the Sons which the Trump
administration further accuses of
providing material support to both
Trenaragua and the Sinaloa cartel in
Mexico their cocaine and fentinel
running operations into the United
States. Thus, the Trump administration
has led the US into designating the
cartel of the Suns as a terrorist
organization as well, which is the
justification that the US government has
used to label Maduro and his inner
circle as narot terrorists and to place
massive bounties on their heads with.
And it might also become the cautious
belli that they use to initiate attacks
on the Maduro government from the
flotillaa that's being assembled off of
their shores. It should also be noted
that there are many, many controversies
surrounding the cartel of the suns,
including as to whether or not it even
exists. Argentina, Paraguay, Peru,
Ecuador, and the Dominican Republic have
all joined the United States and
declared the Cartel of the Suns to be a
terrorist organization. Maduro himself
denies that any such organization
exists. While Colombia's leftist
president, Gustavo Pro, has also
publicly rejected the cartel's existence
and has insisted that it's nothing more
than a propaganda tool being used to
justify toppling Venezuela's government.
Several internal reports in the US also
seem to contradict many of the Trump
administration's claims here. In May, a
National Intelligence Council report
that was declassified concluded that the
Maduro government likely didn't have any
policy of cooperating with Treneragua,
nor did it direct any of Trenderwa's
operations in the United States.
Similarly, the Mexican government has
also said that they have never found any
link between Maduro's government in
Venezuela and the Sinaloa cartel in
Mexico. Nonetheless, the justifications
and cases bellies have been drafted and
the firepower put into place. All that's
required now is to simply pull the
trigger. And on the 2nd of September,
the first shots were fired. A boat
carrying 11 Venezuelans in international
waters that had departed from Venezuela,
was shot by a missile, likely fired by
an American MQ9 Reaper drone, killing
everyone on board. The US government
claimed afterwards that the boat was
carrying a large amount of drugs and
that everyone on board were members of
Trend Neragua, potentially representing
the first instance of a lethal US drone
strike conducted against a Latin
American cartel since Trump returned
back to the presidency. This operation
sharply contrasts with the traditional
procedures the US has used against drug
running vessels in the past, which are
typically intercepted by the Coast Guard
and raided so that their contents can be
verified and their crews apprehended.
Blowing up a suspected drug running
vessel with a drone strike isn't
something that's happened until now, and
it's only added on to the escalation
going on around Venezuela. Since the
Trump administration accuses Maduro's
government of directly maintaining links
to Trend Naragua, adding even more fuel
to the fire, CNN has also begun
reporting that according to multiple
inside sources, the Trump administration
is presently considering initiating
military strikes against cartel targets
within Venezuela itself, which could
ostensibly mean strikes against Trenanga
or against the Venezuelan government
itself, which the Trump administration
claims is essentially indistinguishable
from a cartel. Maduro himself seems to
believe that the US flotillaa gathering
off of his shores are indeed preparing
to attack him and to remove him from
power. He has been freaking out on
social media and in speeches about the
prospect. Has ordered a full
mobilization of his military. Has called
for millions of additional Venezuelan
citizens to join the country's armed
militias to resist any attack. Has
deployed at least 15,000 of his troops
to the border with Colombia. And has
sworn to resist and fight the US to the
bitter end in the event of an actual
attack. On the 5th of September, a pair
of Venezuelan F-16 fighters flew close
to the American warships in a show of
resolve, and the US warned that they
could be shot down the next time if they
were deemed to be a threat. It's really
not an exaggeration at all to say that
the United States and Venezuela have
never been closer to the brink of war
than they currently are now. So, what
exactly is going on here? How did the US
and Venezuela get to this point? What
are the risks of actual conflict both
now and in the future? and will we end
up getting the world we played in during
Mercenaries 2 back in the late 2000s?
It's been building up towards this for
quite some time because the US and
Venezuela have maintained a very
adversarial relationship for pretty much
my own entire lifetime. To give some
historical recap, Venezuela should
realistically be a global energy
superpower because it controls the
largest proven reserves of oil on the
planet, more than even Saudi Arabia. The
oil in Venezuela used to provide the
country with fabulous riches. And as
recently as the 1970s, Venezuela had the
highest GDP per capita in Latin America
because of it. But Venezuela's crude oil
is heavy, sour, and full of impurities
like sulfur. Which means that it's
pretty difficult to refine. Venezuela
was able to gain the technical
assistance it needed with drilling and
refining by attracting major foreign oil
companies like Exxon Mobile, Konico
Phillips, Chevron, and Shell to the
country through joint ventures with
Venezuela stateowned oil company PDVSA.
Oil profits were split 60/40 between
government owned PDVSA and the foreign
energy companies. PDVSA gained valuable
foreign experience and the economic
relationship with the United States
blossomed. And due to the geographic
proximity of the US to Venezuela,
American energy companies built up a
dense network of heavyduty oil
refineries across the Gulf Coast in
Texas and Louisiana that could handle
refining Venezuela's nearby extra heavy
crude, which increased the US Venezuela
relationship even further. By the late
1990s, an overwhelming 60 to 70% of
Venezuela's oil exports were all heading
to the United States, while Venezuelan
oil made up about 15% of all US oil
imports. The single largest source from
any country in the world at the time.
But the huge amount of money that was
gushing into Venezuela through the oil
industry gave way to runaway corruption,
mismanagement, and overdependence.
Between 1972 and 1997, it's been
estimated that as much as $100 billion
dollars was simply embezzled in the
country by hopelessly corrupt government
officials. Meanwhile, oil came to make
up a whopping 90% of Venezuela's total
exports, as much as 70% of the
government's operating budget and up to
40% of the country's entire GDP,
crowding out the development of
virtually all other industries in the
country. In the 1980s, the price of oil
crashed from about $40 a barrel in 1979
to just $10 to $12 a barrel by 1986,
which severely hurt the undiversified
Venezuelan economy. Inflation and debt
in the country both began to soar to
unsustainable levels. And in 1989, the
government agreed to the terms of a
financial bailout from the IMF that
included steep fiscal austerity measures
like decreased subsidies, public sector
layoffs, a currency devaluation, and
increased taxes and interest rates.
Enraged by the fact that the corrupt
government had embezzled billions of
dollars through the stateowned oil
industry and then left its own people to
suffer the consequences through these
austerity measures. The results sparked
a wave of deadly riots across the
country in a sharp increase in
anti-government sentiment. Rioting on
this wave of revolt, a revolutionary
named Hugo Chavez attempted to launch a
failed coup attempt against the
government in 1992. briefly found
himself in prison and then eventually
emerged victorious in the country's 1998
presidential election after running on
an explicitly socialist political
platform with promises that he would
redistribute the nation's oil wealth in
order to help reduce poverty and
inequality. And so began the socialist
experiment in Venezuela that has lasted
for decades ever since. Chavez's
policies, at least initially, actually
were quite successful at reducing the
country's poverty rate. But they also
set in motion the chain of events that
would eventually lead to Venezuela's
almost complete and catastrophic
collapse. Oil production in Venezuela
peaked under his wash in the early
2000s. But after workers at the
stateowned oil company PDVSA began
striking in 2002, he simply fired
thousands of the company's most
experienced workers in the industry
rather than giving into their demands,
which eliminated a huge amount of the
country's technical expertise and
knowhow. He also took steps to almost
completely nationalize the entire oil
industry in the country through seizures
of assets that were owned by the foreign
oil companies like Exxon Chevron and
Konico Phillips which began greatly
straining Venezuela's relationship with
the United States and led to
dramatically reduced foreign investment
in the country which hurt Venezuela's
ability to keep their own refineries and
operations running in the long term. At
almost the same time, he also began
providing heavily subsidized Venezuelan
oil to friendly, largely fellow leftist
states in the region as well, like Cuba
and Nicaragua, which further drain the
country's remaining strategic reserves.
Within just 15 years after being elected
by 2013, Chavez oversaw the country's
national debt more than double while
watching their strategic reserves of oil
dwindle and dwindle. It was an
unsustainable system, but it was also a
popular one that enabled Chavez to
steadily expand the powers of his office
to near dictatorial levels. He
eliminated presidential term limits, and
he had multiple independent media
outlets harassed or even shut down. When
he died in office in 2013, Chavez's
right-hand man and vice president,
Nicholas Maduro, took over the
presidency after him, and he took the
opportunity to rapidly coales his
position into a fullblown dictatorship.
In 2014, just the year after he took
things over, the global price of oil
collapsed again from more than $100 a
barrel to less than $30 a barrel by
early 2016, which threw the Venezuelan
economy that was still cripplingly
overdependent on oil into a tail spin.
Chavez's generous social welfare
policies and subsidies that made him
hugely popular with the people only
worked so long as the price of oil
remained high and Venezuela made lots of
money. Once the oil price collapsed
under Maduro, the nation could no longer
afford its lavish Chavez era
expenditures. Protests and riots erupted
across the country as services and jobs
were dramatically cut and inflation
skyrocketed, to which Maduro responded
to with violence and crackdowns that
immediately diminished his popularity.
In 2015, the Obama administration
declared Venezuela a national security
threat and authorized targeted sanctions
against Maduro and other government
officials. But the true avalanche of
sanctions and the shattering of US
Venezuela relations would come later
during the first Trump administration.
As the political and economic crisis in
Venezuela deepened and Maduro grew
increasingly more autocratic, the first
Trump administration steadily came to
embrace a policy of maximum pressure
against Maduro in an attempt to force
his removal from office through economic
means, especially after the controversy
of the 2018 election in the country.
That year, Maduro claimed to have won
re-election to a second six-year term as
president in an election that was widely
marred by irregularities, the banning of
major opposition candidates from
running, rock bottom turnout, and
accusations of fraud. All of Maduro's
political opponents who ran against him
refused to recognize the 2018 elections
results, as did the US, Australia, the
Organization of American States, and the
EU. At the same time, many of Maduro's
international allies chose to support
him and recognize the results, including
Cuba, Nicaragua, Russia, Bellaris,
China, North Korea, Iran, Syria, and
Turkey, setting the stage for Venezuela
becoming a flash point in the new 21st
century cold war. The first Trump
administration refused to recognize the
election and first declared Maduro to be
an illegitimate usurper when his second
term began in January of 2019. The US
recognized Juan Guyaido, the head of the
country's opposition control national
assembly, as the interim president of
Venezuela instead, severed its remaining
diplomatic relations with Venezuela, and
expelled the country's diplomats from
Washington. Long-standing relations that
had lasted for decades and had been
strained for years were finally
shattered to the point of open
hostility. And on top of all of that,
Trump led the US into unleashing an
avalanche of new sanctions on Venezuela,
too, that were designed to try and
encourage Maduro's removal. Venezuela's
remaining access to the US financial
system was eliminated, which made it
much more difficult for the country to
borrow money and refinance debt. Other
sanctions were designed to target and
strangle the Venezuelan oil industry. US
companies were completely prohibited
from purchasing Venezuelan oil, while
further sanctions targeted companies
that were involved in transporting
Venezuelan oil to third party countries
as well. This eliminated Venezuela's
ability to access the heavyduty oil
refineries around the US Gulf Coast that
they had used for decades to refine
their oil at, while further sanctions
block spare parts and chemicals from
entering into Venezuela to prevent them
from adequately maintaining their own
refineries as well. Coupled with their
own self-induced brain drain of
experienced oil workers fired during the
Chavez years and decades of
mismanagement, underinvestment, and
corruption. The sanctions helped cause
Venezuela's oil production to completely
collapse. And with it, so too did
Venezuela's economy. After 2015,
Venezuelan oil production began falling
off a cliff as the sanctions began to
bite to the point where today Venezuela
is producing less oil than it was back
during World War II. Despite having the
largest reserves in the world between
2014 and 2021 under Maduro's government,
the Venezuelan economy collapsed by an
almost unbelievable three4s. One of the
most catastrophic economic collapses
that has ever been witnessed in modern
history. hyperinflation set in and grew
to as high as 130,000%
by 2018, making the Venezuelan currency
almost worthless in the process. And
while inflation has slowed down since
then, it was still sitting at 190% as
recently as 2023. All of these issues
collectively plunged Venezuela into what
has probably been the country's greatest
civilizational crisis in its entire
history. basic goods and services,
including food, water, and gasoline, all
became preciously scarce. And by late
2022, more than half of Venezuela's
population were reduced to living in
poverty. By far the highest percentage
seen on the South American continent.
And all of this was explicitly designed
to destroy Maduro's popularity and
undermine his legitimacy within
Venezuela and hopefully lead to his
removal from within. But ironically, the
sanctions that Trump dumped on Venezuela
during his first term contributed
directly to the country's unprecedented
migration crisis later during the Biden
administration that he would use as an
issue to help get himself reelected in
2024. Since 2014, close to 8 million
Venezuelan refugees are believed to have
fled the country all around the world,
with many of them heading north towards
the US southern border. By 2021, shortly
after Trump had left office, Venezuelans
became the second most common
nationality, arriving at the southern
border, remaining only behind Mexicans.
And by 2023, the numbers of undocumented
Venezuelan migrants residing in the
United States had increased by nearly
10fold from 2019, around when the heavy
sanctions were first imposed. From only
around 64,000 then, to around 650,000
by 2023. Even worse, for the first Trump
administration, the sanctions didn't
even accomplish their biggest goal,
removing Maduro from power. He
persisted, clinging on to power and
crushed any protests that arose against
him, resulting in the deaths of dozens
to hundreds of protesters since the
contested 2018 election, depending on
the source. And Maduro's isolation from
the US and the Western world led to him
increasing Venezuela's ties with Cuba,
Russia, China, and Iran instead. All of
which helped to buttress his position in
power in various ways. Cuba's
intelligence services began providing
their assistance to him. Russia and Iran
both began providing Venezuela with arms
to replace the loss in American weapons,
while China began buying up most of what
remained of Venezuela's dwindling oil
exports. All of which essentially made
Venezuela second larger Cuba in the
Western Hemisphere from a geopolitical
perspective. And on top of the
sanctions, Trump also put the first
bounty on Maduro during his first term
as well. In 2018, the Trump
administration slapped a $15 million
bounty on Maduro's head based on
accusations that he was personally
directing the operations of the Cartel
of the Suns along with other highranking
Venezuelan military and political
officials. Allegedly, the US government
accused the cartel of the Suns of
utilizing the state apparatus of
Venezuela to run a vast cocaine
trafficking project into the United
States, Europe, and elsewhere as an
alternative source of government revenue
in the face of the US imposed sanctions.
They further accused Maduro and the
cartel of the Sons of collaborating with
the FARC in Colombia to smuggle cocaine
into the United States, an armed Marxist
guerilla rebel force and US designated
terrorist organization with its own
cocaine smuggling operation. Thus, the
US labeled Maduro as a narco terrorist
and charged him with drug trafficking,
moneyaundering, and conspiracy,
regarding him as both an illegitimate
usurper and a wanted fugitive rather
than a sitting president. And then in
between the Trump presidencies, Maduro
continued doing things that kept pissing
off the US government even further.
Initially, the new Biden administration
attempted to ease Trump's maximum
pressure policy towards Venezuela and
reopen engagement. After Russia invaded
Ukraine in early 2022, Biden agreed to
allow Chevron to restart a few of its
operations in Venezuela again in order
to help put more oil onto the market and
reduce prices in order to hurt Russia.
Biden also eased some of Trump's
sanctions on Venezuela in exchange for
political promises. In late 2023, Biden
granted the Venezuelans the ability to
begin exporting their oil and gas again
for a period of 6 months in exchange for
Maduro's promise to hold a free and fair
presidential election the following year
in 2024, which the Biden administration
hoped would succeed at removing him from
power for the maximum pressure strategy
had failed. But almost immediately after
agreeing to host this free and fair
election, Maduro decided to hold a
referendum within the country on whether
or not Venezuela should claim roughly
70% of neighboring Guyana's territory.
Part of a long-standing territorial
dispute that dates back to the colonial
era. This whole situation briefly
captured the world's attention at the
end of 2023 as fears mounted that Maduro
was laying the groundwork for a full-on
invasion of Guyana to claim the disputed
area. If he did so and was successful,
he would also seize control over nearly
all of Guyana's maritime area, and all
of its recently discovered rich offshore
oil reserves that are mostly operated by
Exxon Mobile. Guyana is believed to have
11 billion barrels of oil worth the
reserves offshore, nearly equivalent to
the reserves of OPEC member Algeria. And
because Guyana hasn't been brutally
sanctioned by the US like Venezuela and
generally cooperates with Washington,
Guyana now produces about as much oil as
Venezuela does, despite having vastly
fewer reserves overall. As a result,
Guyana has become a major component of
the global oil and energy map. and most
of its oil exports currently travel to
the US and Europe, helping to keep
Western nation supplies up, keeping oil
prices down with more supply and hurting
Russia and generally benefiting
Washington's overall geopolitical
calculus. A Venezuelan invasion and
seizure of Guyana's territory and oil
fields would never be tolerated by the
US, but Maduro held the referendum for
internal political purposes as well. His
government accused the opposition
leaders in the country of attempting to
sabotage the referendum and issued
arrest warrants for more than a dozen of
them on treason and conspiracy charges,
helping to eliminate many of his most
capable opponents from being able to run
in the 2024 election at all. And so
frustrated, the Biden administration
re-imposed several US sanctions on
Venezuela again in April of 2024, just
ahead of the July presidential election
in the country, which itself became
marred by controversy, just like the
previous 2018 election had. Both Maduro
and his primary political opposition
candidate, Edmundo Gonzalez, claimed
victory in the election. But Maduro
curiously chose not to release any vote
tallies or tabulated results that would
actually prove his victory claim. and
instead he insisted that he narrowly won
the election with just over 51% of the
total. Gonzalez and the opposition
meanwhile claimed that they had actually
won by a landslide and they backed it up
by pretty strong evidence like official
tally sheets that were collected by poll
watchers from a majority of the polling
centers that showed overwhelming support
for Gonzalez. The US along with almost
all of the rest of the Western
Hemisphere, Europe, Australia, New
Zealand, Japan, and South Korea all
refused to recognize the results of the
election and chose to recognize Gonzalez
as the winner in the legitimate
Venezuelan president instead. While
Russia, Belleris, Iran, China, Cuba, and
others chose to support Maduro's claim
and continued recognizing him as the
country's president instead. Anti-Maduro
protests erupted across Venezuela in the
wake of the results, which Maduro used
the army to crush in a massive crackdown
that resulted in more than 2,000 arrests
and more than two dozen deaths. Maduro's
government later issued an arrest
warrant for Gonzalez himself, who fled
the country in exile for Spain, where he
still remains today, a year later with a
continued backing and support of the EU
and US to the Venezuelan presidency.
Maduro had unequivocally become a
fullblown dictator in Venezuela who
openly stole elections without any care
of the consequences. Venezuela's score
on the corruption's perceptions index
correspondingly plummeted, falling by
more than 40 places since 2005 to the
point where it's today ranked as the
third most deeply corrupt country on the
earth. Worse off than even countries
like Syria, Eratraa, and North Korea.
Trump's policy of economic warfare and
sanctions during his first term had
failed to bring about change in the
country and even backfired in the sense
that it contributed to the migration
crisis at the US southern border. While
Biden's policy of engagement and
diplomacy failed to bring about any
change as well, Maduro still remained
throughout at all and if anything was
growing even more authoritarian and
dictatorial, while American influence in
the country was steadily being replaced
by Russian, Chinese, and Iranian
influence instead, giving many of
America's greatest geopolitical enemies
a foothold in the Western Hemisphere. In
the final days of the Biden
administration in January of 2025, he
had the bounty on Maduro's head
increased from $15 million up to $25
million to increase the pressure
further. And then came the second Trump
administration and another shift in
tactics. Initially, Trump tried to
return back to the economic warfare
policies of his first term by cancelling
Chevron's licenses to do any business in
the country. That decision was
championed by a secretary of state,
Marco Rubio, who has long been an
outspoken hawk on Venezuela within
Washington politics. But it was also
condemned by other parties within
Trump's own MAGA movement, like by big
oil interests and by personalities like
Laura Loomer, who argued that the move
surrendered Venezuela's strategic oil
fields to China. By July, Trump relented
to the pressure growing within his own
party and allowed Chevron to continue
their operations in Venezuela. While he
attempted to negotiate with Maduro on
his deportation policies involving the
hundreds of thousands of undocumented
Venezuelans residing within the United
States, Trump sent his special envoy,
Richard Grenel, directly to Venezuela to
meet with Maduro in person. They agreed
that in exchange for a reduction in some
sanctions, Venezuela would release some
American hostages and they would begin
accepting deportation flights of their
citizens from the United States. Through
the month of July alone, the US
government sent nine deportation flights
to Venezuela. a sign of how close
Washington and Caracus were cooperating
together fairly recently. However, Trump
was also aware of three things. His own
policy of sanctions and isolation to try
and remove Maduro from power during his
first term had failed. Biden's policy of
diplomacy and engagement had failed to
remove Maduro from power as well. and
further diplomacy and engagement on his
part was deeply unpopular with large
segments of his own voter base,
especially among the Cuban exile
community in South Florida and his own
secretary of state, Marco Rubio. Trump
has likely calculated that another
tactic to remove Maduro from power or to
force him into compliance was needed
without escalating all the way to
full-blown war. and thus why he has
likely decided to resort to a bout of
gunboat diplomacy now with a secret
directive authorizing the US military to
attack cartels that he's designated as
terrorist organizations his doubling of
the bounty on Maduro's head to $50
million and is surrounding Venezuela's
territorial waters with warships and
submarines not to even mention the
blowing up of the alleged trenda boat
out in international waters Trump is
attempting to apply even more pressure
on Maduro than anyone else has ever done
before getting rid of Maduro the country
and replacing it with a more friendly
regime would do several things for US
interests. First, if it is to be
believed that the cartel of the sons
actually exists and Maduro is indeed
using the powers of the Venezuelan state
to align with Trenaragua and other
cartels to smuggle cocaine and fentinyl
into the United States, toppling him
from power would curb a significant
source of drugs entering into the
country. Secondly, removing Maduro from
power and replacing him with someone
more friendly to Western interests would
remove the Venezuelan territorial threat
to Guyana and all of its oil fields.
While it would also help to restart
Western oil company's activities within
Venezuela itself, which after a few
years time of fixing could help get
massive amounts of Venezuelan oil back
onto the world market again after
decades of absence and neglect, which
would further reduce global oil prices
and help ease inflation and herd
Russia's economy and its warfighting
ability in Ukraine and elsewhere.
Finally, removing Maduro from power
would remove a growing base of
operations for major US adversaries in
the Western Hemisphere. Russia has
announced plans to begin constructing a
major ammunition factory in Venezuela
and has sold billions of dollars worth
of arms to the country and has been
rumored to be considering installing
archnic hypersonic nuclearcapable
missiles on Venezuelan territory as
well, though that so far has been
unsubstantiated. Meanwhile, there's also
been a significant amount of military
cooperation going on between Venezuela
and Iran as well, built upon their
mutual opposition towards the US.
Venezuela has allegedly enabled itself
to be used as a point of entry for
Hezbollah into the greater Latin America
region and the two are known to have
collaborated on drone technology for
years now. Just last year in 2024,
Venezuela unveiled a new kamicazi drone
that they call the Zamora V1, which is
based on the same well-known Shahed 136
drone that has been used extensively by
the Russian army in Ukraine. So far, the
Zamora V1 is much more primitive than
the Shahed 136 is with a much shorter
range and a much smaller explosive
payload. But if the Venezuelans ever
managed to get it up to par with further
help from the Iranians, they could
conceivably eventually use the drones in
swarms to attack strategic targets as
far away as Florida and the Panama
Canal, which is probably a capability
that the United States would not like an
adversary like Venezuela to possess.
With all of that being said, however,
the number of military assets that Trump
has so far deployed around Venezuela are
not enough for a full-blown invasion
into the country. But that's probably
not what Trump is actually wanting to do
anyway. It is still the largest overseas
deployment of US military assets in the
Western Hemisphere since the 1989
invasion of Panama. But Venezuela in
2025 is not the same thing as Panama in
1989. Back then, the US had similarly
indicted Panama's dictator, Manuel
Noriega, on federal drug trafficking
charges and decided to invade the
country in order to remove and arrest
him. But that operation involved nearly
30,000 US troops, many of whom were
already stationed directly in Panama
near the Panama Canal Zone back when it
still existed. And Panama was a much
smaller country with a much smaller
population than Venezuela has today.
Only 4,500 US troops have so far been
positioned around Venezuela aboard their
ships. Far too few to actually invade
the country, remove Maduro from power,
and occupy it. But that isn't to say
that they can't still help remove Maduro
from power anyway. Trump is likely
betting that following the hotly
disputed 2024 election and protest in
the country, the Maduro is presently
deeply unpopular with his own people.
The $50 million bounty on his head and
the tens of millions of dollars on his
crony's heads along with the presence of
all the US warships gathered just
offshore might just tempt someone to
launch a rebellion with the expectation
that the US warships and air power will
give assistance to them. Giving the US
the ground forces that it needs without
having to commit any of their own.
Similar to how NATO air power helped
Libyan rebels on the ground topple
Muamar Gaddafi's regime in 2011. If a
similar series of events were to
transpire in Venezuela, the US also
already has the man in waiting that they
would want to replace Madura with.
Edmundo Gonzalez still in exile in Spain
whom Washington still recognizes as
Venezuela's legitimate president. The
tomahawk missiles on board the
destroyers, cruiser, and submarine along
with the F-35s known to be deployed to
Puerto Rico enables the United States to
decide on surgical aerial strikes
against Maduro's most critical assets
and infrastructure. They could choose to
attack narcotic sites or even elements
of the state like military and command
sites or even Venezuela's remaining
operational oil production and refinery
sites. They could even resort to
attempted decapitation strikes targeting
Maduro himself and/or his senior
generals and officers. The Marine
Expeditionary Unit, while not large
enough to assault the beaches and march
all the way to Caracus and arrest Maduro
alone, could also be utilized in a more
limited raid under extensive aerial
cover to attempt an arrest and
extraction of Maduro under certain
circumstances. Like in the event of a
major rebellion and its associated chaos
in the country, doing something like
this would be far from unprecedented for
Trump and would in fact represent his
preferred way of deploying US military
power. During his first administration,
he ordered Tomahawk missile strikes
against the Assad regime in Syria in
2017. He ordered a special forces raid
in Syria in 2019 that killed the leader
of ISIS. And it's recently come to light
that he also authorized a failed Navy
Seal raid into North Korea that resulted
in three killed North Korean civilians.
In 2020, he authorized a drone strike in
Iraq that assassinated Iran's most
senior military commander. And already
in 2025, he's launched a sea and air
campaign against the Houthis in Yemen
and ordered a B2 bomber raid on Iran
that blew up Iran's most critical
nuclear research sites. Trump doesn't
like getting involved in big land wars.
But he does like employing surgical air
strikes and raids. And the forces he has
gathered just outside of Venezuela could
fit this pattern of his with limited
strikes against the Maduro regime itself
or against Trenaragua and other cartel
targets. To give you an idea of the
current capabilities of the Venezuelan
military, consider the fate of the
Venezuelan Navy's patrol boat, Neuada,
in 2020. While operating in
international waters, the Neuada
attempted to intercept a cruise ship
called the RCGS Resolute. The
Venezuelans fired warning shots and
ordered the Resolute to follow them to a
port in Venezuela before they then
collided their ship with the Resolute
and sank themselves without anybody on
the Resolute ever doing anything at all.
Maduro himself then denounced the
captain of the Resolute as a pirate and
a terrorist. While the Venezuelan
defense minister described what happened
as an act of imperial aggression on the
part of the Resolute, a cruise ship.
Venezuela has some fighter jets, tanks,
warships, and submarines and their
Iranian assisted drones. But the
sanctions that have been levied upon
them for years have prevented them from
acquiring spare parts and performing
routine maintenance on a lot of them.
And while Venezuela is known to have the
Russian-p produced S300 anti-air system
that dates back from the 2000s, it's
likely that America's more modern F-35
fighters that are currently in Puerto
Rico could evade their detection. While
the S300's would also struggle against
the Tomahawk cruise missiles as well. If
Trump gives the order for the flotilla
to begin launching aerial attacks at
targets within Venezuela itself rather
than just limiting them to drug runners
out in international waters, there's
likely little the Maduro could
realistically do to actually stop them.
Whether that results in a rebellion or
Maduro's removal from power, however, is
a different thing entirely. There were
great hopes within Israel and the United
States that the aerial bombing campaign
launched against Iran earlier this year
would have led to a rebellion that would
topple the Iranian regime as well. But
that never ended up materializing. And
if anything, foreign bombs falling on
Iranian soil only solidify the regime's
authority with its people. There is no
guarantee that attacks on Venezuela
would do anything different. And then
even if it does end up working out as
intended and Maduro does end up getting
removed, there's no guarantee of what
the ensuing chaos in Venezuela could
produce. Tobling Gaddafi in Libya and
Saddam in Iraq both led to decades of
chaos in those countries. And armed
non-state actors in Colombia like the
ELN, who have extensive influence in
Venezuela, could capitalize on the chaos
produced in unpredictable and
potentially undesirable ways. Venezuela
could end up developing into a situation
like a in neighboring Colombia, which
has been experiencing a constant
low-level conflict between various
non-state militias and armed groups for
the past half century now.
Interestingly, just before I release
this video, the Venezuelan government
began accusing the US of conducting
intelligence flights over the Caribbean
region against them. Venezuela's defense
minister, who has that active $15
million bounty on his head issued by the
US government, stated that American
intelligence and reconnaissance
operations, including spy flights
against Venezuela, had tripled across
the month of August. This led to the
defense minister claiming that the US
was seeking a justification for an armed
intervention in Venezuela to remove
Maduro from power. And since then, one
of the US Navy warships reportedly
raided a Venezuelan fishing boat within
Venezuela's own waters. the first
apparent search and seizure operation by
the Navy Force that's gathered in the
region. I've been a longtime user of
Ground News and I've partnered with them
since 2022 because it's a product I
trust to give me the information I need
to better understand how a story is
being framed and the context behind it.
Ground News is an app and website on a
mission to give us the transparency
we're looking for in the news. It pulls
in thousands of articles every day from
all around the world into one place to
show us how the different outlets cover
the same story. So for each story, you
get a visual breakdown of each outlet's
bias, its reliability, and who owns the
source. Let me show you how it works. On
ground news, you can see that over 250
news outlets are covering this story
with the majority leaning left and
center. And if I scroll down, I can see
every outlet that's reported on the
story. Venezuela and left-leaning
sources have called the seizure of the
fishing boat illegal and have described
it as a hostile raid that violated
Venezuela's national sovereignty, while
the US government and right-leaning
sources have stressed it as a necessary
action of US anti-drug enforcement and a
justified seizure within a law and order
context. This story was also a blind
spot for people who read right-leaning
sources. Ground News has an entire
feature they call the blind spot feed to
make sure you don't miss out on any
stories that are being
disproportionately reported by either
side of the political spectrum, like
this one we just saw. I use ground news
daily and as a critical research tool
for my videos. I find it crucial in
today's increasingly polarized media
environment. And as viewers of my
channel, I think you'd find it extremely
valuable, too. Which is why I've
partnered with Crown News to get you 40%
off of their unlimited access Vantage
plan if you subscribe through the link
down below in my description at
ground.new/realifeelore
or by scanning the QR code that's here
on your screen as well. It's the same
plan that I use. Ground News and I share
the same mission. And by checking them
out, you'll also be supporting my
channel as well. And as always, thank
you so much for watching.