These pictures are tiny — book-page
woodcuts you could hold in your hand, not
the vast frescoes that once sprawled
across the walls of medieval churchyards.
For centuries they've been filed under a
calm, dutiful label: a memento mori, a
polite reminder that everyone, sooner or
later, must die.
And yet, hidden inside the sequence, there
is a single image that quietly turns the
whole thing inside out — that takes what
looks like a sermon and reveals something
far closer to a weapon.
The series is called The Dance of Death.
It was designed by Hans Holbein the
Younger — who lived from 1497 to 1543
— while he was working in Basel, somewhere
between 1523 and 1526.
Holbein drew the designs; the astonishing
fineness of the cutting belongs to a
master block-cutter named Hans
Lützelburger, whose work has been called,
quite simply, the most marvelous woodcuts
ever made.
By most accounts Lützelburger died around
1526, before the book ever reached print —
the craftsman who gave Death its face met
Death first.
The first edition appeared in Lyon in
1538, published by the Trechsel brothers
under a French title — Les Simulachres et
Historiées Faces de la Mort, the images
and storied faces of death — and it
held forty-one woodcuts.
People could not get enough of it.
There were eleven editions before 1562,
and across the century perhaps a hundred
more unauthorized copies and imitations.
An old churchyard tradition had been
shrunk down, printed, and let loose across
Europe.
When you first leaf through the series,
the premise looks simple, even repetitive.
Into one ordinary moment after another — a
throne room, a study, a day in the
fields — strides the same uninvited guest:
a skeleton.
Death has come, and Death always wins.
But look at how he behaves, and the
simplicity falls away.
Holbein's Death is not a solemn, hooded
reaper.
He is a performer, and the joke is
always tailored to his victim.
He turns into a kind of dispenser of
justice — denouncing greed and the abuse
of power.
He robs the rich man of his money
before he takes his soul.
He boldly hauls an abbot away by his
vestments.
He skewers a knight.
For the nobility, Death arrives as an
opponent who simply cannot be beaten.
In one scene after another, he doesn't
merely take the powerful — he mocks the
very thing they lived for, and more often
than not he holds up an hourglass to
do it.
That little glass runs through the series
like a refrain.
And then he reaches the people who never
had any power at all — and something
strange happens to his manner.
To feel why that matters, step back into
the world that made these prints.
The "dance of death," the danse macabre,
was already an old idea — a procession
of the living led away by the dead,
painted across the walls of charnel houses
so a whole town could file past it.
Its message was blunt and democratic:
whatever your rank, Death is the great
equalizer, and every class distinction is
wiped out the moment he takes your hand.
Holbein inherited that idea — and
sharpened every edge of it.
He was working in Basel in the 1520s,
a city right on the fault line of
the Reformation, and what he made was less
a gentle memorial than what scholars call
a reformist satire: the old allegory,
re-pointed.
And now we come to the Ploughman.
Among all these scenes of Death the
tormentor — Death the thief, Death the
mocker, Death who drags an abbot and
unseats a king — there is one that
is utterly different in tone.
A peasant works his field behind a team
of tired horses at the end of the
day.
And the figure beside him, helping to
drive the horses on, helping him finish
the very last furrow — that figure is
Death.
Here he is not a thief at all.
He is a companion.
He is almost a kindness, easing an
exhausted man toward the end of his row,
toward rest.
Sit with the contrast.
For the pope, the rich man, the knight,
Death is an ambush and a humiliation.
For the man who owns nothing but his
labour, Death is mercy.
The same skeleton, the same series, the
same artist — and two opposite meanings,
depending entirely on which rung of the
ladder you happen to stand on.
So which is the real Dance of Death?
Here the interpretations split, and both
have weight.
The traditional reading is the gentle one.
This is a memento mori: Death comes for
everyone, pope and ploughman alike, so
prepare your soul, because status counts
for nothing in the end.
Pious, universal, and perfectly at home in
a prayer book.
But notice who Death visits, and how.
He marches the pope, the cardinal, the
bishop, the abbot, the emperor and the
king to the front of the procession, and
he saves his cruelest jokes for exactly
the people who claimed to stand above the
crowd — and closest to God.
Read that way, the series stops being a
soft reminder of mortality and becomes a
reckoning: Death as the one honest
official who cannot be bribed, flattered,
or outranked.
And yet — and this is where it
stays honest — Holbein doesn't simply hate
the Church.
Look closely and you'll find that the
humble preacher and the parish priest
escape his sarcasm entirely; they're shown
in sympathy with the poor.
His scorn isn't aimed at faith.
It's aimed at power.
That, perhaps, is the real trick of these
little pictures.
The very same book could sit on a
bishop's shelf as a devout meditation and
circulate among reformers as a joke at the
bishop's expense.
The piety is the disguise; the protest is
the payload — and both are completely true
at once.
Holbein understood that the most
unsettling thing you can show the powerful
is not that they will die.
They knew that.
It's that when they die, they will be
exactly equal to the peasant in the field
— and that the peasant, of the two,
may be the one who finally gets to
rest.
So I'll hand the question to you.
When you look at Holbein's skeleton —
dragging the pope from his throne, and
helping the ploughman home — do you see
a preacher reminding us all of our end?
Or a satirist, smuggling a quiet
revolution inside a prayer book?
Tell me how you read it.
Thank you for looking this closely with
me.