Inflation is plummeting. Incomes are
rising fast.
>> Every single metric out there is saying
that the economy is stronger than ever.
GDP is growing, low unemployment, and
stocks are at all-time highs.
>> The roaring economy is roaring like
never before.
>> So then, why does it feel like none of
that is true? Because the stock market
hasn't been measuring your life for
almost 100 years. In fact, what we have
now are two completely different
economies running inside the same
country. Okay, but why should you care?
Well, because now the same companies,
the same jobs, and the same industries
are splitting in half depending on which
side you're on. And so, clearly that
impacts all of you, so you can't just
sit this one out. Because the people who
built this system made sure you can't
tear it down without holding you
hostage. I've spent weeks uncovering
their playbook, and I'll break down this
entire thing in a way that's actually
easy to understand. And by the end of
this video, you'll understand why making
more money won't save you, but I'll tell
you exactly what will.
So, everyone's arguing about whether the
economy is good or bad with these
record-high stock prices, but that's the
wrong question. Because the stock market
was never designed to measure whether
your life is getting better, it measures
something else entirely. So, let's start
by breaking it down in a simple way.
First and foremost, the economy measures
everything. And I mean everything from
trade to production, and it's usually
measured by things like GDP,
unemployment, inflation, and consumer
spending. Whereas the stock market
doesn't really directly measure any of
that. A better way to look at it,
especially now, is where investors trade
bets on how much money companies will
make in the future. And so, it's a bit
of an oversimplification, but that's it.
And another thing to know is that the
S&P 500, which is what everyone points
to when they say that the market is up,
only tracks about 500 companies out of
the 30 million businesses in America.
So, really it's again talking about a
very thin slice of the actual economy.
If you don't believe me, this also isn't
the first time that the stock market is
telling a completely different story
while reality is telling another. And
every time it's happened before, it's
ended up the same way. I'm sure a lot of
you have heard about the Roaring
Twenties. And as the name suggests, it
was this golden era
on paper. Between 1922 and 1929, the Dow
had gone up six times in eight years,
and the economy was growing almost 5% a
year while unemployment was only under
4%. So, it was roaring all right, but
underneath all of that were some cracks
on paper. Farmers were actually drowning
in debt. Factories were producing way
more product than they could sell, and
most of the market's growth wasn't
coming from real businesses. It was
coming from people borrowing money to
place bigger and bigger bets on stocks
going up. Sound familiar? Well, in 1929,
the stocks did stop going up. The Great
Depression hit, wiping out 80 to 85% of
the stock market value, and soon enough
production collapsed by nearly half, and
unemployment hit one in four Americans,
leading to the worst economic collapse
that you all know about, but here's the
thing that you may not know. Just a few
years after the crash, the stock market
started rallying back nearly over 300%
between 1933 and 1937. So, again, on
paper, it was like America was so back.
But the thing is, that was again just
the stock market. While many ordinary
Americans still stood in breadlines, and
recovery wasn't really a reality for
most. So, that was almost 100 years ago,
and it's one of the earliest and
clearest examples of the stock market
and the economy telling completely
different stories. And today, the S&P is
at all-time highs while consumer
confidence is near pandemic lows. So,
the question becomes, why does this keep
happening? Well, there's a few reasons,
but one in particular stands out, and it
starts with what I considered the
biggest bet in human history. If you
watch any of my countless videos on AI,
you know that Big Tech right now is in
the middle of the largest spending spree
in corporate history, from data centers
to infrastructure. And comparing it to
previous bubbles, it's now more than
triple than what the entire telecom
industry spent at the peak of the
dot-com boom. But with that said, that
sounds great, right? Especially when the
economy is factoring in consumer
spending and investment. So, it must
mean that growth is happening. But if
you hear the words from Goldman Sachs
chief economist, he said it and broke it
down the best. When asked about how much
AI spending actually boosted the economy
in 2025, his answer was basically zero.
>> Our estimate, AI investment didn't
affect US GDP growth.
>> Because most of the hardware is
imported, so it doesn't even count
towards American production. The money
flows out, the stock prices go up, and
the GDP number barely moves. So,
remember, the economy isn't growing
because of AI, the stock market is
growing because of AI. Like I
established, those are two very
different things. But again, that isn't
even the biggest reason. Because the
real engine has been burning since 2008.
A feedback loop that we gotten so
addicted to as a country that truly
explains why the stock market and
economy no longer matches up. Before
2008, the Fed wasn't really pumping too
much money into the financial system.
Roughly around $800 billion, but that
number hasn't really changed over the
decades. But then when the crash
happened, the Fed started a panic, and
as a Fed does, by controlling monetary
policy  interest rates to near
zero, and for the first time ever
started increasingly pumping and
printing more money, whereby 2014 that
$800 billion has grown to $4.5 trillion.
And this addiction is called
quantitative easing, but all you need to
know is that the Fed was creating money,
pumping it into financial markets like
stocks, bonds, and real estate, causing
stock prices to shoot up. But again,
those were just assets, not wages or the
value of the dollar. And just like a gin
or a nicotine gum addiction, you say
it's only just once in a while, start to
showing signs of real habit.
Because a few years later in 2017 when
they stopped trying to do this
quantitative easing, well, the market
started crashing, so they reversed
course and brought it back. And once
that recent pandemic hit, that $4
trillion now doubled to $9 trillion in 2
years, and it's exactly why stocks have
ballooned during this time. And not to
mention, with all that money printed
meant inflation hitting the highest in
40 years, but who who cares about that?
But what's clear is that this loop now
became an addiction. And every time the
economy started showing signs of slowing
down, the dose got bigger and bigger.
The Fed prints more money, money flows
into stocks, the people who own stocks
feel richer. Let me Let me take this
out. They spend more, that spending
shows up in GDP, and politicians call it
a strong economy. And just as we're
seeing now, it's now something they
can't even stop. It's a full-blown
addiction because every time they try to
pull back, the market drops, and so just
like a withdrawal, they put it right
back.
I was actually going to light this for
this video, but probably shouldn't
inside of this apartment. But anyways,
stock market has become a wealth engine
that runs on a completely different
track. But what's clear is that a system
like this doesn't just sustain itself by
accident. And when you follow the money
to find out who exactly benefits from
keeping it this way, you'll start to see
why nothing ever changes. And part of
understanding how money actually works
starts with understanding your own. But
most people struggle with this because
everything is scattered across different
apps, statements, and accounts. And
that's exactly why I use today's
sponsor, Monarch Money. It's a private,
ad-free personal finance platform that
syncs with over 13,000 institutions and
brings everything into one clean
dashboard. You can watch all your
accounts, spending, net worth, and
recurring bills in one place. And what I
like about them specifically is that
they give a lot of clarity without all
the micromanaging. I have ADHD, I can't
deal with that. You can separate fixed
and flexible spending, set savings or
payoff goals, and track your net worth
over a period of time. And Monarch also
uses AI-powered insights to explain your
account changes in simple language, so
you understand what's happening without
constantly having to check. So, if you
want a calmer, clearer way to manage
your money, scan the QR code or use the
link in the description to try Monarch
Money today. So, back to it because I'm
now proving to you how the stock market
and economy are different. And a big
reason why is that addictive feedback
loop that we got into addicted to. But,
what I found are three players that are
now feeding into each other to keep this
loop running forever.
So, let's start at the top, the CEOs.
So, for most of the 20th century, stock
buybacks were illegal and for good
reason. Because if a company uses its
own money to buy its own stock, the
price obviously goes up and anyone with
a brain will think that's textbook
manipulation. But, in 1982, they quietly
changed that rule and since then,
buybacks have become one of the most
powerful tools in corporate America. And
something that allows the soul and blood
of America, the stock market, to keep
going up. So, let me just show you
exactly what I mean. Between 2019 and
2024, Lowe's, like the hardware store,
spent $46.6 billion buying back its own
stock. And yeah, big number, but that
works out to roughly $28,000 per
employee while the average Lowe's worker
made around $30,600.
So, if you view it like that, the
company was literally spending almost as
much as inflating its own stock price
than paying its entire workforce. But
I'm not just picking on Lowe's. The 100
lowest paying companies in the S&P 500
spent a combined $644 billion on
buybacks over that same exact period.
And you might be asking like, why? Why
would a CEO choose to inflate the stock
price instead of investing in the
company? Well, it's because over 80% of
the CEOs now get paid from stock awards
and stock options. So, when the stock
price goes up, the CEO gets paid a lot
more. And it's pretty much that simple.
So, if we're going to be real here, is
it fair to just blame the CEOs when
that's really just the incentive
structure at play? And incentives are
always going to reveal outcomes. So,
before you go in the comments and start
calling me a bootlicker, what I'm trying
to get at is that the CEO can't just do
this alone. In fact, they have bosses,
too. And not to mention, someone has to
be buying those inflated stocks, and not
just buying them, but holding them, and
even encouraging it. Which brings me to
the second player, and these companies
here sit at the center of all of this.
BlackRock, Vanguard, and State Street
are all asset management companies, and
they manage over $24 trillion.
And not just that, they're the largest
single shareholder in 88% of S&P 500
companies. And with that amount of
power, it means that these three firms
vote on behalf of millions of investors
at corporate shareholder meetings. Which
means that they have a lot of say on
things from, let's say, CEO compensation
packages or buyback programs. And guess
how these asset management firms make
their money? They charge fees on the
percentage of total assets, which means
exactly what you might be tracking. So,
anytime the stock market goes up, their
revenue goes up automatically. So, these
same three firms that make more money
when stock prices rise, are also the
same people who vote on whether CEOs can
keep inflating stocks with buybacks. Of
course, they're never going to vote no,
considering every buyback inflates the
assets that they collect fees on, and
voting against buybacks would be voting
against their own revenue. So, those are
the two players, but there's one more
player that keeps this whole thing
protected because none of this works
without someone writing the rules to
allow it. When Nancy Pelosi took office
in 1987, her portfolio was worth
somewhere between like $600,000 and
$800,000, but today it's worth $133.7
million.
That's a 16,930%
gain, and it's not even close in how
much they beat out the S&P, the NASDAQ,
and the Dow over the same exact period.
But, I think you all know this by now.
Over 100 members of Congress make 10,000
stock trades every year, and and it's
not like this right or left thing
because both Democrats and Republicans
consistently outperform even
professional money managers. And just to
protect myself, allegedly and in my
opinion, these members are routinely
trading stocks with insider information
on companies that their committees
directly oversee. So, I think a lot of
you already know this, but here's what
most people miss. Again, to protect
myself, it's not just about, allegedly
and in my opinion, insider trading in
Congress, it goes even higher. Because
think about it, how do we measure
whether a president is doing a good job?
It's usually the stock market. That has
become like the scorecard now for
success, and every president knows this.
I've analyzed a lot of Trump's and
previous presidents' speeches, and Trump
himself has pointed to the stock market
more than almost everything else as
proof that his policies work. And of
course, I'm recording this just as the
war has broken out, but usually the
approval ratings and the market's
performance tend to move together. When
the market is up, approval ratings are
high, and when it dips, he's kind of
But, where I'm going with this is that
Wall Street knows this, too. They know
that no president, regardless of party,
can ever afford to let the market crash.
So, what this means that every CEO doing
buybacks and every asset manager
collecting fees know that they have
pretty much unlimited protection. They
can keep inflating prices because the
government can't afford to stop them and
tell them no. So, you can now start
seeing how this is all circular and
connected. The president needs the
market up to prove that the economy
works. The market needs the president to
keep the rule favorable. And as long as
both sides need each other, nothing
changes. And to put a little tiny bow on
top of that, it's exactly why 26 out of
42 Wall Street lobbyists last year were
former government employees. So, it's
not even two separate groups of people
anymore. They're all the same damn
thing. Just like the addiction that we
talked about earlier, the longer this
loop runs, the harder it becomes to
break. Because breaking it wouldn't just
hurt the people at the top, it would
crash the same retirement accounts and
pensions that regular people depend on.
So, it's not crazy to say that this
system has now made you hostage, and I
can prove that, too.
But the thing you need to understand
first is that the economy is strong, and
that's not a lie. Every single one of
those numbers is real. But to understand
this, what nobody tells you is who those
numbers are actually measuring. Because
if you're going to be held hostage, you
also need a hostage taker. And what
we're starting to see is two completely
different economies running inside the
same country. And someone much smarter
than I am had put it into words better
than I could. In September 2025, Mark
Zandi, the chief economist at Moody's
Analytics, updated his data on who's
actually spending money in America. And
his conclusion is kind of scary. As you
can see in this tweet, "Looking at the
data, it's not a mystery why most
Americans feel like the economy isn't
working for them. For the bottom 80%,
those making less than about $175,000
a year, spending has just kept pace with
inflation since the pandemic, which
means that it didn't really grow, it
just matched price increases. But if you
compare that to the top 3.3%, in Zandi's
words, what it's showing is that they're
doing much much much better. But like,
duh. Of course, if you have more income,
you're going to be able to spend more,
but so what? Well, remember how the
economy measures everything? When
consumer spending in the US makes up
about 70% of our GDP, I mean, [ __ ] like
we love to consume. What this
essentially means is that 10% of people
are driving 50% of all that, which
essentially means that the GDP looks
strong on paper, but that growth is
largely being driven from one group's
stock gains and home equity. But still,
just throwing numbers at you is still
abstract. Until you see what I'm talking
about being played out in the real
world. Because what we're now seeing is
that companies have noticed the split,
and they're actively picking sides.
Believe it or not, in the early 2000s,
McDonald's was like in this death
spiral, where sales were failing and so
was its stock. But then they came up
with this brilliant idea to introduce
the dollar menu. Remember those? It's
obviously built for low-income consumers
who needed to make the most bang out of
their buck, and it worked. McDonald's
revenue shot up 33%, and as we know them
today, built
on affordable food for everyone. But
fast forward to 2025, and that's quietly
no longer the case. The McDonald's CEO
has recently told investors that traffic
from low-income households to McDonald's
has dropped by nearly double digits, and
it's because 78% of Americans now view
fast-food restaurants like McDonald's as
a luxury. And instead, what he's seeing
is that high-income visitors have
skyrocketed. And as I looked even
closer, what I found is that this is
basically happening to every industry in
America, and everything is splitting in
two. Even traditional low-cost retailers
like Walmart are seeing similar trends.
Luxury hotels like Four Seasons and
Ritz-Carlton are posting nearly 3%
higher revenue, while economy budget
hotels have dropped 3.1%. Airlines are
rapidly building up luxury suites with
caviar service, and a problem that
they're facing is that it's overcrowded,
while economy seat demand has started to
shrink. So, what's becoming more and
more clear is that we're looking at what
economists call a K-shaped economy,
where one line goes up and the other
goes down and even under the same system
in loops is a sharp increase in two
completely different outcomes depending
on which side of the K you are on. And
so you might be thinking as long as
you're on top of the K, who cares, but
this is why it should scare everyone
because if things don't change, it's
only going to keep affecting everyone.
As our homie Zandy puts it, right now it
doesn't feel like the economy's perched
on a strong foundation. It's perched on
a few poles that are sticking up and if
one of those poles gets knocked out,
then the whole economy gets knocked down
and it's scary because he's right. The
stock market right now is being carried
by a handful of tech companies investing
heavily in AI. Job growth is being
carried almost entirely by the
healthcare sector and consumer spending,
remember 70% of GDP, is again being
carried only by the top 10% and when
that top 10% is continuing to own more
and more stocks to a tune of around
624,000 more than just 3 years ago
because the stock price keeps going up
and up, now the question becomes what
happens if the market and when it
corrects. And as I'm writing this,
especially with what's going on with the
war, if this now leads to some sort of
collapse and they start pulling back
their money, there's not really going to
be anything underneath to catch that
fall. And I haven't even mentioned the
middle class that used to be the
backbone of this economy and country and
there's a reason why there isn't any
even space for them on the K and it's
because the middle class is actively
shrinking. What used to be 61% in 1971
is now 51% today and most of those
people falling out of the middle class
aren't moving up, they're sliding down
in the bottom bar. And like I talked
about earlier, we've already seen this
movie with the Great Depression where
the asset class will inevitably benefit
from the crash and recovery while even
years after the non-asset class stood in
breadlines. And what scares me most is
that right now the S&P 500 and consumer
sentiment are forming that exact same
shape. So what's clear is that even with
this strong economy that we see today,
what it doesn't describe is the 330
million people that make up this
country. What it more so describes is
the 33 million. But, hey, at least the
Dow is over 50,000, right? So, now the
question becomes what's next? I mean,
it's pretty clear that this isn't a
broken system waiting to be fixed. And
when you consider that this has been a
working system since the age of kings
and queens or at least the Great
Depression, truth is, it will always
probably be this way. But, what I'm
actually trying to say here is that this
actually means hope. Hope that if the
system is always going to be designed
this way, once you see it, you can
actually start to use it. Because if the
people running our economy is indeed
addicted to this loop that I explained,
what becomes obvious if you want to
escape this permanent underclass is that
the difference between the two economies
is an income. 41% of people today making
between 300,000 to 500,000 a year say
that they're living paycheck to
paycheck. And when I looked even closer,
40% of people making over 500,000 are
saying the same thing. So, what's clear
is that now more than ever the line
isn't income, it's ownership. Because if
the system is set up where if you own
assets, the current carries you, and if
you don't, no matter how much you make
or work hard, it will always pull away
from you. So, obviously, what I'm saying
is easier said than done. And in fact,
it's only getting harder. But, as I
record this video right now from
Croatia, what I'm constantly getting
reminded is that for all of America's
problems, that door is still open wider
than any other country on Earth. So, I'm
not going to lie to you and say that I'm
not trying to join that upper part of
the K. But, I know for certain that the
more I understand how this works, the
more I know to my heart that I can only
do it in a way that's ethical and
honest. So, if you do have a problem
with me wanting to escape the permanent
underclass, you should unsubscribe right
now, and I mean it. I do not want you in
my audience. Because in a world of money
and power, the people who understand the
game will always do better than the
people who refuse to acknowledge it. And
that's exactly who I'm making these
videos for.